<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Divine meditations. Written by an honourable person. Whereto is adjoyned, a determination of the question, whether men ought to kneele at the receipt of the Holy Communion. And an essay of friendship</title>
            <author>Wake, Isaac, Sir, 1580?-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66095</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W226B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831338</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831338</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66095)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2118:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Divine meditations. Written by an honourable person. Whereto is adjoyned, a determination of the question, whether men ought to kneele at the receipt of the Holy Communion. And an essay of friendship</title>
                  <author>Wake, Isaac, Sir, 1580?-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 162, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. Badger, for Humphrey Mosley, and are to be sold at his shop at his shop at the Princes Armes, in S. Pauls Church-Yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An honourable person = Sir Isaac Wake.</note>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf: Imprimatur. Tho. Wykes. R.P. Episc. Lond. Capell: Domest.</note>
                  <note>"An essay of friendship." has a separate title page dated 1640; register and pagination continuous.</note>
                  <note>Copy has print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35801:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Divine MEDITATIONS. WRITTEN By an HONOURABLE PERSON.</p>
            <p>Whereto is adjoyned, a Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Queſtion, whether Men ought to Kneele at the Receipt of the <hi>HOLY COMMVNION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And an <hi>Eſſay</hi> of <hi>FRIENDSHIP.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dat Roſa mel apibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Badger,</hi> for <hi>Humphrey Moſley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Princes Armes in S. Pauls Church-Yard. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group xml:lang="eng">
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35801:2"/>
                  <head>A MEDITATION upon PSAL. 91.</head>
                  <q>I. <hi>Who ſo dwelleth under the defenſe of the moſt High, ſhall abide under the ſhadow of the Almighty.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> exhibites here matter of ſingular comfort to all ſuch as can well underſtand it, and <hi>rightly apply</hi> it to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35801:3"/>But wee muſt bee carefull that wee runne not too faſt to the <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> leſt we deceave our ſelves, and thinke wee are ſafe under the <hi>defenſe of the most High,</hi> when perhaps wee are in the <hi>ſhadow of Death.</hi> All men naturally <hi>beleeve eaſily</hi> what they <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſtrongly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quod nimis miſeri vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, hoc fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile credunt <hi>Senes.</hi>
                     </note> and there's no <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> ſo dangerous, as when men deceive their <hi>owne ſoules,</hi> and think they are ſafe, when they are in danger. Many runne bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God with <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> in their mouth, as if they were his Children, who ſhal receave for anſwer, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcio vos,</hi> I know you not, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22, 23. This is a ſpirituall <hi>Phrenſie,</hi> not unlike
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35801:3"/>that of the mad-man in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> who ſeeing any Ship arrive ranne ſtraight to the Haven and tooke an <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory</hi> of all the Lading, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining it to bee <hi>his owne,</hi> when he had no part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Wee muſt therefore ſtudy to know who are thoſe that <hi>dwell under the defence of the most High,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee can conclude who ſhall <hi>abide under the ſhadow of the Almightie.</hi> This Point is excellently cleered by the ſame Prophet, who ſeemed to comment on this Text, in the fifteenth <hi>Pſal.</hi> demanding in the firſt <hi>Ver. Lord who ſhall dwell in thy Tabernacle,</hi> or <hi>who ſhall rest on thy Holy Hill?</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving the queſtion in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35801:4"/>words following to the end of the Pſalme: <hi>Even hee that leads an incorrupt life, and doth the thing that is right, &amp;c.</hi> Thus let the true Chriſtian examine his <hi>owne heart,</hi> and conſider whether his life hath been or is <hi>incorrupt:</hi> whether he doth the things
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>See Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char.</hi> 7. <hi>ver</hi> 9, 10</note> that <hi>are right:</hi> whether hee ſpeake the truth <hi>from his heart;</hi> whether hee hath uſed no deceit with his <hi>Tongue,</hi> nor done evill to his <hi>Neighbour, &amp;c.</hi> (as it followes there) and then he may conclude with <hi>David</hi> in the laſt words of that <hi>Pſal.</hi> that he ſhall <hi>never fall,</hi> having <hi>done theſe things,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that he <hi>dwells un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35801:4"/>the defence of the most High.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is likewiſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Rule,</hi> by which wee muſt examine our ſelves, and that is properly mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to us in the Phraſe which the Prophet uſeth of <hi>dwelling</hi> under the defenſe of the moſt <hi>High:</hi> It is an ordinary expreſſion in the Scripture, that God <hi>dwells</hi> with his Elect, and they with him: and theſe are <hi>Relatives</hi> which cannot ſtand one without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hee then that would know whether hee dwell under the defence of the moſt <hi>High,</hi> muſt ſee, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God <hi>dwell</hi> with him. Of this, no man can bee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35801:5"/>ignorant;
<note place="margin">Fruits of the Fleſh and Spirit, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.9.</note> for where the Spirit of God is, it will <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare</hi> and make it ſelfe knowne; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> declares what are the <hi>Fruits of the Spirit,</hi> viz. <hi>Love, Ioy, Peace, Long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Gentleneſſe, Goodneſſe, Faith, Meekeneſſe</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance:</hi> and likewiſe, what are the <hi>Fruits of the Fleſh.</hi> viz. <hi>Adultery, Fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Uncleanneſſe, Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Idolatry, Witchcraft, Hatred, Debate, Emulation, Wrath, Contention, Sedition, Hereſies, Envie, Murther, Drunkennes, Revelling,</hi> and ſuch like. Hee that will <hi>ſit in Iudgment on himſelfe,</hi> and examine which of theſe Fruits ſpring out of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35801:5"/>heart, ſhall ſoone know, whether <hi>God</hi> dwell in him, or the Devill. For the eyes of God cannot behold im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity: He is (all) purity and ſanctity, and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will not inhabit a <hi>pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Temple.</hi> If therefore, thou finde thy Heart and Soule to be corrupt and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, know that it is a <hi>Cage of uncleane Birds,</hi> and no fit <hi>Tabernacle</hi> for God. But if thou have waſht away thy filthineſſe by Repentance, and the <hi>Bloud of Chriſt hath clenſed thee from all ſinne,</hi> then maiſt thou bee ſure, that God is with thee, and that thou <hi>dwellest under the Defence of the most High,</hi> and maiſt boldly goe on with <hi>David,</hi> and ſay:</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35801:6"/>
                  <q>2. <hi>I will ſay unto the Lord; Thou art my Hope and my ſtrong Hold: my God; in Him will I trust.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>If any man would have a <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> upon theſe words, hee may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the 18. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and ſay with <hi>David</hi> there; <hi>The Lord is my ſtrong Rock, and my Defence, my Saviour, my God, and my Might in whom I will truſt, my Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, the Horne alſo of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and my Refuge.</hi> In the 144. <hi>Pſalme</hi> ver. 2. the ſame Prophet calls GOD <hi>his hope,</hi> and his <hi>fortreſſe,</hi> his <hi>Castle</hi> and <hi>deliverer,</hi> his <hi>Defender, in whom hee will trust, Pſalme</hi> 31. ver. 3. he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35801:6"/>ſtiles him his <hi>ſtrong Rocke,</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Defenſe:</hi> and verſe 4. his <hi>ſtrong Rocke,</hi> (againe) and <hi>Castle, Pſalm.</hi> 62. ver. 2. <hi>Hee verily is my ſtrength and ſalvation: hee is my defenſe,</hi> ſo <hi>that I ſhall not greatly fall:</hi> which words are repeated, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. Through the whole <hi>Body of Scripture,</hi> there is <hi>nothing</hi> more frequent then ſuch like expreſſions of Gods power to ſecure <hi>his children</hi> from any danger whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: and Exhortations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them to rely upon him without
<note n="*" place="margin">Doubting of Gods mercy, or providence, is not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham ſtagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not at Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity, but was ſtrong in Faith, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying God: <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. And Iacob ceaſed not to wreſtle with the ANGEL, though his thigh were bruiſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.26.</note> Doubting, and to truſt in him <hi>as a faithfull Creator.</hi> Is he a <hi>Rock?</hi> then pray with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>O ſet mee on the Rocke that is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35801:7"/>higher then I, Pſalm.</hi> 61.3. Follow our Saviours coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. and <hi>Build thy Houſe on the Rocke:</hi> which nor <hi>ſtorme of winde,</hi> nor <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of Water,</hi> ſhall ever be able to ſhake. Is hee thy <hi>Hope?</hi> then maiſt thou be ſure, he will not <hi>faile thee:</hi> for hee never did forſake thoſe, that put their truſt in him. Is he thy <hi>ſtrong hold?</hi> Feare then no perſecution of any enemy whatſoever. For no Battery can make breach in <hi>this Castle,</hi> nor any craft of <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Devill</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine it. This Fortreſſe is <hi>God,</hi> in whom onely <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> truſted, who having created the World, and all that is therein, commands and over-rules all his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35801:7"/>ſo that nothing ſhall offend thoſe his Children, whom hee hath taken into his protection. Yea <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> himſelfe ſhall tempt <hi>Iob</hi> no further then <hi>God</hi> ſhall permit him. Some put their truſt in <hi>Chariots and Horſes,</hi> but they are <hi>brought downe and falne, Pſalme</hi> 20. But wee that remember the <hi>Name of the Lord our God,</hi> are riſen and ſtand upright. Ver. 7, 8. O then <hi>trust not in Princes, nor in any child of man, for there's no helpe in them,</hi> Pſalme 146.2. <hi>Nothing can be ſaved by the multitude of an Hoſt; nor is any Mightie man delivered by much ſtrength, Pſal.</hi> 33.15. Wherefore, <hi>bleſſed is he that hath the God of</hi> Iacob
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35801:8"/>
                     <hi>for his helpe, and whoſe hope is in the Lord his God, which made Heaven and earth, the Sea, and all that therein is, which keepes his Promiſe for ever, Pſalm.</hi> 146. For, they <hi>that put their trust in the Lord, ſhall be as Mount Sion, which may not bee removed, but ſtandeth faſt for ever.</hi> Who ſo can with a true and lively Faith anchor his hopes on God <hi>in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> may boldly repoſe in him, and reſt ſecure in all Time of Danger, Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Tribulation.</p>
                  <q>3. <hi>For hee ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and from the noiſome Peſtilence.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35801:8"/>
                  <q>4. <hi>Hee ſhall defend thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Wings; and thou ſhalt bee ſafe under his Feathers: his Faithfulnes and Truth ſhall bee thy ſhield and buckler.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
                     </label> The particle <hi>For,</hi> may ſeeme to ſome to come a little <hi>too cloſe</hi> after the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer words; <hi>I will ſay to the Lord, Thou art my hope and ſtrong hold, my God, in him will I truſt: For, hee ſhall deliver thee, &amp;c!</hi> As if he would not truſt in God, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he were <hi>ſure</hi> of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Iob</hi> ſeemes to ſpeake more <hi>reſolutely:</hi> ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave <hi>Good</hi> at the hands of God, and not <hi>Evill? Iob</hi> 2.10. ſhall the Child of God, thanke him and truſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35801:9"/>in him onely for <hi>Bleſsings,</hi> and not for <hi>Afflictions</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo? God forbid. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God doth unto us, muſt be accepted thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe it proceeds from him, be it Bleſſing, or Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. <hi>Is there any evill in the City, that I have not done?</hi> ſaith the Lord by the Prophet: and ſhall we therefore ceaſe to bleſſe, praiſe, and magnifie him, becauſe he viſits and afflicts us? Not ſo. This (for) is not <hi>conditionall,</hi> but <hi>illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> The Pſalmiſt here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs the godly, to whom to have recourſe in <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous times:</hi> and as in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſes he ſhewed, that their Protector is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, that it is God, who
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35801:9"/>is their <hi>ſtrong Hold,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declaring his <hi>Power:</hi> ſo here hee ſpecifies his <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe</hi> and <hi>Readineſſe</hi> to defend and protect his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and cauſally exhorts all Gods Children to truſt in the Lord: <hi>for,</hi> or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</hi> as he is their <hi>ſtrong Hold</hi> and their God <hi>in whom they truſt:</hi> ſo hee will and ſhall deliver them in all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents of danger. Were that particle <hi>(For) conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall</hi> (as it is not, but illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive) yet were there no
<note n="*" place="margin">The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, thogh wee are to live by ſaith, yet a dram of tried faith, is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a pound of untried.</note> 
                     <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruity.</hi> For when <hi>Iacob</hi> went towards <hi>Laban,</hi> hee did in a manner <hi>ſtipulate</hi> with God, ſaying, <hi>If God will bee with mee and keepe mee in this way I goe, and will give mee Bread to eate,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35801:10"/>and Rayment to put on, ſo that I returne to my Fathers houſe in peace, then ſhall the Lord be my God, Geneſis</hi> 28.20, 21. So may every good Chriſtian being in danger, neceſſity, and Tribulation, pray to GOD for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, comfort, and ſupply of his Wants; and vow, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did, that if God will bleſſe him and deliver him, then hee ſhall bee his God and Lord, and that he will feare, honour and ſerve him, and him only: which vow hath no <hi>negative Implicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that if GOD deliver him not, <hi>then</hi> hee ſhall <hi>not</hi> bee his God. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> underſtood this perfectly; as is evident by his often thanking God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:35801:10"/>for afflictions, and Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. he ſaith firſt; <hi>O Lord thou haſt dealt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly with thy ſervant; for before I was troubled, I went wrong: but now I have kept thy word.</hi> And preſently after: <hi>It is good for me that I have beene in trouble, that I may learne thy ſtatutes:</hi> and in Pſalme 16. <hi>I will thanke thee Lord for giving me warning, ver.</hi> 8. After that manner, throughout the whole book of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> he frequently expreſſes his thankefull acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Afflictions, Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and Perſecutions. Here he inſtructs the godly in whom to truſt, namely in God: aſſuring them, they may boldly doe it: <hi>for,</hi> or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35801:11"/>
                     <hi>becauſe,</hi> he will or ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſnare, &amp;c.</hi> that is, from all Perſecutions of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſpirituall or temporall. Our ſpirituall Adverſary is the <hi>devill,</hi> who may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly termed a <hi>Hunter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, beſide his owne dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wicked ſuggeſtions, he doth by the Vanities of the <hi>World,</hi> and the luſts &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> lay nets and ſnares to entrap us. Truſt firmely in God, and hee will deliver thee from this formidable enemy, who goes about like a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lion,</hi> ſeeking whom to devoure. At the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he got the ſtart of our firſt Parents, when ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie made them forfeit their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35801:11"/>Innocencie, by <hi>yeelding to his Temptations.</hi> But God preſently roſe and ſhewed himſelf, paſſing ſentence ore that ſeducer, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. <hi>I will put Enmitie betweene thee and the woman: and betwixt thy ſeed, and her ſeed: hee ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This enemy is moſt to be feared, becauſe his ſnares are moſt dangerous, he dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plowing with our <hi>owne Heifer,</hi> and fomenting our <hi>Fleſh</hi> in her Rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſo that if God were not our <hi>Hope and ſtrong Hold,</hi> it were impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for us to eſcape. But if in him we truſt, God will breake his ſnares, and our Soule ſhall bee delivered
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35801:12"/>
                     <hi>as a Bird out of the ſnare of the Fowler: Pſalme</hi> 144. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. Let Satan ſeeke to <hi>winnow</hi> us, as hee did Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> we have <hi>Chriſt</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercede for <hi>us,</hi> as hee did for <hi>him,</hi> that our <hi>Faith faile not.</hi> Truſt then in this Advocate, be not wanting to thy ſelfe, but put on the <hi>whole Armour</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the <hi>Shield
<note n="*" place="margin">It was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of a Souldier to be diſarmd of his Shield.</note> of Faith,</hi> which may quench the <hi>fiery Darts of Satan, Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. As for <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall dangers</hi> and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they are leſſe to be feared, for hee that hath a care of thy <hi>Soule,</hi> will preſerve thy <hi>Body,</hi> ſo that no Enemy ſhall hurt nor Danger overwhelme thee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35801:12"/>Of all Temporall Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, thoſe that touch the Body, and threaten the Life, are moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; as the Devill, though a Lyar from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſaid truely, <hi>Skinne for skinne, and all that a man hath, will he give for his Life. Iob</hi> 2.4. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing endangers life, more than the <hi>Plague</hi> or <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> againſt the dread and danger whereof, this Pſalme ſeemes more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to bee dictated. That this very Affliction is the greateſt of all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Afflictions, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by <hi>David,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his choice of <hi>War, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> and <hi>Peſtilence,</hi> out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35801:13"/>a true ſenſe and feeling of his great ſinne, choſe the
<note n="*" place="margin">[Herein the learned Author fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes <hi>Ioſephus.</hi>]</note> 
                     <hi>greateſt puniſhment,</hi> and ſuch a one as is <hi>unavoidable</hi> by greatneſſe, or any tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall helpe, the cure wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or preſervation from it, depending
<note n="*" place="margin">Ther's no ſpecificall Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Peſtilence: (as Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans confeſs.) <hi>Vid. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer. de Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>immediately on God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Angell</hi> ſtrikes where he commands, and ſpares thoſe whom hee would have preſerved. It is a ſwift flying <hi>Arrow</hi> that lights on us <hi>unawares,</hi> and commonly ſtrikes at the heart. Witneſſe, the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who were all deſtroyed by it, in one night the Army of <hi>Senna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi> of whom the Angell of the Lord ſlew 185000. (by the Peſtilence) in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther night; and the muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:35801:13"/>murmuring <hi>Iſraelites</hi> who were ſmitten in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For no ſooner had <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Wrath</hi> is gone out from the Lord, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately 14700. died of the <hi>Plague, Num.</hi> 16. It is <hi>noiſome,</hi> and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, <hi>uncomfortable,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving men of ſuccour, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, or reliefe; ſo that he who is <hi>viſited</hi> therewith may truly ſay with <hi>David; My loynes are filled with a ſore diſeaſe, and there is no ſound part in my Body,</hi> Pſal. 38.7. Adde hereunto out of the ſame Pſalme: <hi>My lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Neighbours did ſtand looking on my trouble, and my Kinſmen ſtood a far off.</hi> It is a <hi>Terror,</hi> and that by night, when ſmall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:35801:14"/>ſeeme great, and great apprehenſions are terrible. But as it walkes in <hi>Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> which is dreadfull, ſo it flies by <hi>Day,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroies likewiſe at Noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; not only <hi>affrighting,</hi> but <hi>aſtoniſhing,</hi> and <hi>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing</hi> us with fearefull <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles</hi> of <hi>Mortality: as thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that fall beſides us; and tenne thouſand at our right hand. It reſpects no perſons,</hi> as wee ſee by example of <hi>Ezekias,</hi> who being a King, and a good King, was ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with viſited. There's no avoyding it, becauſe it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds <hi>immediately from God,</hi> from whom thou canſt not flye. <hi>Whither ſhall I goe from thy Spirit,</hi> or <hi>from thy preſence? If I climbe up to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35801:14"/>Heaven, thou art there; if I deſcend to Hell, thou art there alſo, Pſal.</hi> 139. Is there then no remedy? muſt wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of helpe or comfort, in this time of <hi>Mortality?</hi> Is there no <hi>Balme in Gilead?</hi> yes ſure. When <hi>Naaman</hi> had the <hi>Leproſie,</hi> a Captive Mayd told her Maiſter: <hi>Would God, my Lord were with</hi> the Prophet that is in <hi>Samaria:</hi> for he would recover him of his Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5. Could a Prophet cure the Leproſy? Then remember there is here a greater then any Prophet. See what a <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</hi> the Pſalmiſt hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, what <hi>Antidote</hi> he miniſters againſt this dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diſeaſe. The <hi>Phyſitian</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35801:15"/>is God Omnipotent, who will <hi>defend thee under His Wings, ſo that thou ſhalt bee ſafe under His Feathers.</hi> The <hi>Antidot</hi> and Preſervative, is thy Hope &amp; Affiance in Him.
<note n="*" place="margin">Credere, eſt extra nos ire, &amp; in Chriſtum tranſire.</note> Repaire then to that Phyſitian, take that <hi>Antidote,</hi> and thou ſhalt not be afraid for any ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour by night, nor for the Arrow that flies by Day? <hi>A thouſand ſhall fall beſide thee and tenne thouſand at thy right hand, but it ſhall not come nigh thee.</hi> Pray then for Faith and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God, and nothing ſhall diſmay thee. <hi>God is our Hope and ſtrength, a very preſent Helpe in Trouble: therefore will we not feare, though the Earth be moved,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35801:15"/>or the Hills throwne into the midſt of the Sea. Pſalme</hi> 42.1, 2. Doth not the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tell thee in this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> that <hi>His Faithfulneſſe and Truth ſhalbe thy Shield and Buckler?</hi> He hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee to invocate Him <hi>when thou art in Trouble,</hi> and promiſed to <hi>deliver</hi> thee <hi>Iames</hi> 5.13. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 50.15. <hi>Returne to the Lord thy God, and be obedient to His Voice, He will not forſake nor deſtroy thee. Deut.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Caſt thy Burden on the Lord, and Hee ſhall nouriſh thee. Pſal.</hi> 55.22 <hi>Come to me</hi> (ſaith He) <hi>all yee that labour, and are heavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden, and I will refreſh you. Mat.</hi> 11, 28. Conſider then, <hi>with whom thou haſt to deale,</hi> and bee confident of His
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35801:16"/>Clemency, who is ſo <hi>rich</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Men oft falſify: but God wilbe as good as His Word.</note> in mercy, ſo <hi>bountifull</hi> in His promiſes, and ſo
<note n="*" place="margin">See Rom. 10.12.</note> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and <hi>punctuall in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> of His Word. If His fidelity and verity be thy <hi>Shield</hi> and <hi>Buckler,</hi> thou haſt a good and <hi>warrantable Ground</hi> for thy Hope and Truſt in Him. For <hi>God,</hi> is not like <hi>Man,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>lie,</hi> nor like the Sonne of man, that He ſhould <hi>repent:</hi> but immutable and <hi>without variation.</hi> His promiſes are yea and Amen. Hee will not ſuffer His <hi>Truth to faile,</hi> nor <hi>breake His Covenant;</hi> nor <hi>alter the thing that is gone out of His mouth. Pſalme</hi> 89.33, 34. He hath beene <hi>ever mindefull</hi> of His Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Promiſe, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35801:16"/>He made to a <hi>thouſand Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. Pſalme</hi> 105.8. His word cannot be <hi>fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated Eſay</hi> 55.11. <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe, but My Word ſhall not paſſe away,</hi> ſaith our Saviour. <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.35.</p>
                  <p>Having therefore in this <hi>perillous</hi> time of the Plague, ſuch a Phyſitian at hand, who can and will either cure or preſerve us, we may reſt <hi>ſecure</hi> under His wings, and <hi>ſafe</hi> under His Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; if we will. Beware; that wee bee not like the <hi>Iewes,</hi> of whom our Saviour ſpake: <hi>O Ieruſalem, Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, how oft would I have ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered thy children together, even as a hen gathers her chickens under her Wings,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35801:17"/>and ye would not. Matth.</hi> 23.37. If chickens runne from under the wings of the hen, no mervaile, if the <hi>Kite</hi> ſeize on them. Since then thou haſt in this Danger, the <hi>Wings</hi> of God for thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and His <hi>Feathers</hi> for thy ſafety, keepe thee there, without wandring after vaine pleaſures, for feare of being caught.</p>
                  <p>And ſince our Phyſitian hath preſcribed us ſuch <hi>Soveraigne Antidotes and Preſervatives,</hi> it muſt be our care to uſe them
<note n="*" place="margin">Cum debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to regimine as Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſay.</note> 
                     <hi>according to His Preſcript:</hi> The <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients</hi> of this <hi>Diacatholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> are <hi>Faith, Hope, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> and <hi>Prayer.</hi> No Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction or viſitation befalls us, but as a <hi>chastiſement</hi> or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35801:17"/>
                     <hi>puniſhment</hi> for ſin. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that would be freed of the <hi>Paine</hi> which hee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, muſt endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the <hi>Cauſe:</hi> whereto he muſt put <hi>his owne helping hand,</hi> and apply to himſelfe thoſe <hi>ſalves</hi> that are proper for his <hi>Sore. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> was not cured of his Leproſie, till he had waſhed himſelfe ſeven times in <hi>Iordan.</hi> Doe thou <hi>every night</hi> waſh thy Bed, and water thy Couch with thy <hi>Teares: Pſalme</hi> 6.6. and then thou ſhalt be cleane likewiſe. When the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked God, and pulled downe the Plague upon themſelves, <hi>Moſes</hi> percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that wrath was gone
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35801:18"/>out from God, commanded <hi>Aaron</hi> to take a Cenſer and put Incenſe therein, and <hi>quickely
<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 16.46.</note> to make an Attonement</hi> for the People. When wee ſee <hi>Gods hand</hi> neere us, or over us, or feele it in our ſelves, wee muſt <hi>preſently</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Zec. 8.21.</note> ſeeke to make an Attonement, and offer to Him, <hi>first</hi> the Calves of our lips, which is, Thankes, for having <hi>given us war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> and <hi>next,</hi> the ſacrifice of a broken and <hi>contrite</hi> heart which he doth never <hi>deſpiſe.</hi> When the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne of <hi>Egypt</hi> were ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to kill a
<note n="*" place="margin">This Lamb was a type which prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured Chriſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Lambe,</hi> and ſprinkle it's Bloud on the Lintells of their Doors; that the <hi>miniſteriall Angell,</hi>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35801:18"/>ſent to puniſh the <hi>Egyptians</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing the <hi>Bloud of the Lamb</hi> on their Doores, might paſſe over them and doe them no hurt. In this <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> the Angell of God, the executioner of His Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, is abroad: they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that deſire to be <hi>ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> muſt by Faith appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the merits of Ieſus Chriſt, and have their <hi>ſoules</hi> ſprinkled with His Bloud; elſe how can they hope or truſt in God, or have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in His Protection, being not reconcil'd to Him by His Sonne? Nor having by a true and lively Faith apprehended the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of His Paſſion and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied them to themſelves? It is true our Saviour hath
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35801:19"/>promiſed to eaſe thoſe that labour and are heavie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; but <hi>conditionally,</hi> if they <hi>come unto Him;</hi> which is done, <hi>by Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> Wherefore in ſo dangerous a Viſitation, when the Defence of the moſt High is ſo neceſſary, and our Truſt in Him ſo comfortable, let us <hi>be ſure</hi> that <hi>our Hope be well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on Faith;</hi> and pray <hi>without ceaſing,</hi> for <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Penitence,</hi> which are Graces that we cannot attaine of our ſelves, but are <hi>gratis datae,</hi> and cannot be obtained but by <hi>fervent</hi> Prayer. Hee then that by Prayer and <hi>Repentance often renewed,</hi> hath got <hi>ſenſible Encreaſe</hi> of the ſaving
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35801:19"/>Graces of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> may ſafely and ſincerely truſt in God for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from the Plague; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by taking <hi>it away from him,</hi> or <hi>him from it:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Faith with out Repeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, a meere mock Faith.</note> which latter, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> accounts <hi>farre better;</hi> deſiring to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> and to <hi>be with Chriſt:</hi> Death being to the Godly, a Reſt to the body, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to the ſoule; which is freed from falling into ſinne, and admitted to the <hi>bliſſefull Vnion</hi> of her Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and Redeemer.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, in time of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, and Vengeance, when the deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell is abroad with his <hi>Sword drawne,</hi> it is no ſmall comfort to a Chriſtian man, when <hi>Thouſands</hi> fall
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:35801:20"/>beſide him and <hi>tenne thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> at his right hand, to be preſerved from Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. His comfort may well be encreaſed and doubled, in contemplation of Gods mercy
<note n="*" place="margin">See this excellently expreſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. 30.18.</note> and goodneſſe to him. Yet, muſt we take heed of paſſing <hi>raſh Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> on thoſe that are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited by Gods hand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding our ſelves to bee <hi>more righteous then they.</hi> Our Saviour taught His Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples <hi>another Leſſon</hi> (<hi>Luk.</hi> 13) upon occaſion of the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilaeans,</hi> whoſe Bloud <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices; and of thoſe, on whom the Tower of <hi>Siloe</hi> fell: telling them, that they were not greater ſinners then other men: and except
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35801:20"/>
                     <hi>they repented, they likewiſe ſhould periſh.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Counſell, is ſeaſonable: <hi>Let him that ſtands, take heed leaſt he fall:</hi> and his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is worthy our Imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; profeſſing himſelfe, to bee the <hi>Greateſt ſinner,</hi> though hee were an <hi>elect Veſſell.</hi> When therefore wee ſee Gods Iudgements powred upon
<note n="*" place="margin">What then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> are we better then they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> No; in no wiſe. Rom. 39.</note> others, let us not <hi>fondly</hi> and <hi>raſhly</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them, as more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly then we are, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that we have deſerved as much as they, and thanke him, for having ſpared us and given us <hi>a longer Time of repentance.</hi> Give glory to God for ſhewing mercy to thee, which thou <hi>deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedſt not,</hi> when his wrath
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:35801:21"/>was powred on others, which perhaps <hi>deſerved it leſſe</hi> than thou. Improve the Time lent thee, to <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, Contrition,</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of Life.</hi> Be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and fervent in praier. <hi>Let the Lord be thy Hope,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Ioel. 3.16</note> let thy faith be <hi>operative</hi> by works of Piety and <hi>Charity Gal.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ 9.10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 5.6. and then ſhall no evill happen unto thee: for <hi>Hee ſhall give His Angells charge over thee, to keepe thee in all thy wayes: &amp;c.</hi> Theſe Angels, being Spirits, are not to be ſeene by the eye of Faith, but when by Gods order, they aſſume Bodies; and therefore we muſt looke up with an <hi>eye of Faith</hi> to Him who rules and commands them, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35801:21"/>hath made them all, <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſpirits, ſent forth for the behoofe of them who are heires of Salvation. Heb.</hi> 1.14. and therefore when the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, executioner of Gods juſtice, is abroad, we may hope and truſt in God, that His Angells <hi>encampe</hi> about us that feare and worſhip Him in ſinceritie of heart.</p>
                  <p>In the eighteenth of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> we reade of <hi>three An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> that appeared to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the ſhape of men, and from him they went to deſtroy <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah:</hi> yet, in the nineteenth, wee finde mention but of <hi>two Angels</hi> that were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by <hi>Lot,</hi> and did execute the vengeance of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35801:22"/>God on thoſe ſinfull Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: Some have obſerved, that God Almighty, who was one of the three that appeared to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and miniſtred occaſion to him to pray for <hi>Lots</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, did afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, and leave to his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, the execution of His juſtice: and that through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Scripture God Himſelfe is never recorded to ſhew Himſelfe <hi>viſibly,</hi> but when Hee glorifies Himſelfe <hi>in Mercy,</hi> ever committing the executing of <hi>Iudgements</hi> to His mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. This Conceipt is ſtrengthened by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Interpretation of the Parable of the <hi>Teares: Mat.</hi> 13. where Hee ſaies <hi>that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35801:22"/>the Officers which are to burne the Teares,</hi> are <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: Pſal.</hi> 39.41, 42. which <hi>in the end of the world Hee will ſend forth, to gather out of His Kingdome all things which offend, and them which doe Iniquity,</hi> and <hi>to caſt them into a Furnace of fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When the Devill temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Saviour, had ſet Him on the Pinacle of the Temple, he perverted part of this Pſalme, to perſwade Him to ſhew Himſelfe to be the Sonne of God by caſting Himſelfe downe: for (ſaith he) it is writen, He will give his Angels charge over thee, that thou hurt not thy foote againſt a ſtone. <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the third is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35801:23"/>to have followed the Devill <hi>very cloſe,</hi> applying to Himſelfe the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, &amp; <hi>abuſing</hi> them like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when he ſet his foote on the neck of the Emperor <hi>Fredericke;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt goe upon the Lion and Adder, the young Lion</hi> and <hi>the Dragon ſhalt thou tread under thy feete.</hi> This had no conformity with the Doctrine of our Saviour, nor with the practiſe of Himſelfe and His Apoſtles. <hi>He</hi> paid Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not <hi>trode</hi> on his necke. But I will not amplifie this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancy. Tranſeat inter cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros errores Canoniſtarum:</hi> and let that Pope paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that <hi>detort</hi> Scripture to their owne
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35801:23"/>Damnation. Let us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, we ſtumble not at the <hi>ſame ſtone,</hi> by miſinterpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<note n="*" place="margin">See a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sermon preached at Oxford by Maſter Iohn Hales, the rare Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton College</note> or miſapplying Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>careleſly</hi> and <hi>negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as Satan did <hi>ſubtilly</hi> and <hi>maliciouſly.</hi> God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven His Angels charge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, <hi>that they beare us in their hands &amp;c.</hi> but they are bound to keepe thee, <hi>but in all thy wayes:</hi> (which words the Devill omitted, becauſe they made not for his purpoſe.) This point is clearely demonſtrated in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> from their <hi>Exit,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> till their Entrance into <hi>Canaan.</hi> For as long as they were <hi>in their way,</hi> and were obedient to the word of the Lord, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:35801:24"/>could hurt them; as appeares by their <hi>miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Deliverances</hi> from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and <hi>frequent victories</hi> over all their enemies: But when they went <hi>out of their way, by murmuring, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Idolatry,</hi> then were they ſtung
<note n="*" place="margin">Num. 21.6</note> with fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery <hi>ſerpents,</hi> and ſould into the hands of their <hi>Enemies,</hi> or ſmitten with the <hi>Plague:</hi> none of Gods Angels com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, to helpe them, till they returnd <hi>into the way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,</hi> by <hi>Repentance.</hi> The Royall Prophet oft <hi>harpes</hi> on this ſtringe in the Booke of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> which Saint <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary</hi> truly calles <hi>The Key of Scripture.</hi> If we peruſe the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> 44.18.80.106. we ſhall ſee the <hi>Iewes</hi> proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35801:24"/>and flouriſhing under Gods Protection while they walkt <hi>in their way;</hi> and dejected and abandoned, when they ſtarted aſide <hi>like a broken Bow.</hi> While <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> haire was uncut (which was his Vow of a <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi>) his ſtrength was unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable; but when he went <hi>out of his way</hi> to <hi>Timnah</hi> (<hi>Iud.</hi> 14.1.) and <hi>Delilah</hi> had cut his Lockes, though he went out againſt the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> (as at other times) God having left him, they prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. When <hi>Saul</hi> ſinned, the Spirit of God departed from him. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.14. <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> the beſt King that ever raigned in <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> never went out of his way <hi>(for ought We read)</hi> but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35801:25"/>once, when he would needs fight with <hi>Pharoah-Necho,</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who had no quarrell to him, and then, as if God had <hi>watched him</hi> to take him in his <hi>first fault,</hi> he miſcarried, and was ſlaine. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 35. Let us then take heede how wee goe with <hi>Ionas</hi> to <hi>Tharſis,</hi> when we are commanded to goe to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> leaſt we draw a bitter ſtorme on our ſelves and thoſe that are in our company. The <hi>wayes</hi> we are to walke in, if we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the protection of God, and Aſſiſtance of His holy Angels, are traced out unto us in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> where we are taught what <hi>to doe,</hi> and what <hi>not to doe.</hi> The Old and New Teſtament
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35801:25"/>are <hi>Commentaries</hi> on theſe tenne Commandements: and therefore we muſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, read, and meditate Gods word, if we deſire to know His <hi>Will</hi> and to doe it. <hi>David</hi> askes the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion: <hi>Wherewithall ſhall a young man cleanſe his way?</hi> and inſtantly reſolves it: <hi>Even by ruling himſelfe by thy word.</hi> This word is a <hi>Lanterne</hi> to our way, and a <hi>Light</hi> to our Paths: <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119: in which <hi>Pſalme,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in <hi>every Line,</hi> there is mention made of the <hi>word, Law, Statutes,</hi> and <hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements</hi> of God; wherein the Prophet deſires to be inſtructed, and profeſſes to be ſingularly delighted. Since then our way is <hi>chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:35801:26"/>out</hi> in Gods word, let us pray with the Prophet, <hi>Order my ſteps in thy word, ſo ſhall no wickedneſſe have dominion over me. Pſal.</hi> 143. <hi>Teach me O Lord the way of thy Statutes, make me to goe in the Paths of thy Precepts. Pſalm.</hi> 119. If we can <hi>thus</hi> pray with a <hi>pure heart,</hi> God will anſwer us; as <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 32.9. <hi>I will informe and teach thee, in the way wherein thou ſhalt goe, and I will guide thee with mine Eye.</hi> If by <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> we can pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe this Grace from God to be guided and directed <hi>in our wayes,</hi> and if we looke to our ſteps, and be carefull not to goe out of the way, when he hath ſet us in, we may reſt aſſured of His
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:35801:26"/>gracious providence, and angelicall protection in our <hi>ſeverall vocations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But O Lord, <hi>What is man, that thou art mindfull of him; and the ſon of man, that thou viſiteſt him, Pſal.</hi> 8.4. <hi>Thou madeſt him lower than the Angels,</hi> and yet <hi>thou commandest thy bleſſed Angels to attend him, to have charge over him, and to beare him
<note n="*" place="margin">As Nur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es be are young children in their arms: (So the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports.)</note> in their hands!</hi> What moveth thee O Lord to be ſo gracious and ſo good to <hi>this poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of thine?</p>
                  <q>14. <hi>Becauſe he hath ſet his love upon me, therefore ſhall I deliver him: I ſhall ſet him up, becauſe he hath known my Name.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:35801:27"/>
                  <q>15. <hi>He ſhall call upon mee, and I will heare him: Yea, I am with him in trouble; I will deliver him, and being him to honour.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>16. <hi>With long life will I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie him; and ſhew him my ſalvation.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>The <hi>cauſall Particle</hi> here <hi>(Becauſe)</hi> iterated Verſ. 14. is not to be underſtood as if it implied any <hi>Merit</hi> in us, or as if God were <hi>obliged</hi> in regard of our knowledg of him, to protect us from the Peſtilence, or to make <hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Dragons</hi> ſubject to us, as he did to <hi>David, Daniel,</hi> and others of his children: but hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence <hi>ſimply</hi> and <hi>purely</hi> to his mercy and goodneſſe,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:35801:27"/>who hath a ſpeciall care of his Elect (whom he covers under his wings in all times of danger) and to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe which he hath made, to reward <hi>freely,</hi> and not for any deſert, thoſe that <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely</hi> love him, and <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> invocate him. If we deſire the honour to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>his Sonnes,</hi> are we not bound to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> him whom we call Father? Can we doe leſſe than love God the <hi>Father,</hi> for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us after his owne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage? God <hi>the Sonne,</hi> for <hi>redeeming</hi> us when we were loſt? God the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for alwayes <hi>comforting</hi> and aſſiſting us? And when we have done <hi>our beſt,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Deus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur affectu, quam effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu. Amb.</note> are we not <hi>unprofitable</hi> ſervants?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:35801:28"/>Herein is love (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) not that <hi>we loved God,</hi> but that <hi>he loved us,</hi> and ſent his Sonne to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation for our ſinnes, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.10. And indeed, how could we poſſibly love him, if he had not given us the grace to know him, and conſequently to love him? <hi>Ignoti nulla cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido.</hi> Now although we can claime no <hi>merit</hi> by our loving of God, (becauſe it is our bounden <hi>Duty</hi>) yet are we well encouraged thereto, by the <hi>Reward</hi> which accompanies it, in vertue of Gods <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and of his <hi>pure Mercy</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe.</hi> In the ſecond <hi>Commandement</hi> he promiſes to ſhew mercy to <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands,</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:35801:28"/>in them that love him, and keepe his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. <hi>O love the Lord all ye his Saints, for the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves them that are faithfull,</hi> &amp;c. As therefore it is our duty to expreſſe our <hi>grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> (for graces or benefits received) by loving God who conferres them: ſo is it an Act of Gods <hi>meere goodneſſe,</hi> to love us for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him, and to make us ſee and feele the effects of his love, by his preſervation and protection. <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 130.4. ſaith, <hi>There is mercy with thee, therfore thou ſhalt be feared:</hi> which may ſeeme to have ſome repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, with the love for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſpoken of, in that <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:35801:29"/>men <hi>hate</hi> thoſe whom they <hi>feare. Oderint, dum metuant.</hi> This is true among <hi>Barbarians,</hi> and thoſe that are oppreſt by <hi>Tyrants.</hi> But we muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt a ſervile and filiall feare. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is proper to the <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,</hi> the latter to the <hi>elect.</hi> There is no childe of God that will not feare to offend and diſpleaſe his heavenly Father, that hath beene ſo indulgent and gracious un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, as he muſt needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and confeſſe, if he have any ſenſe of God or godlineſſe, or any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his ſtupendious creation, redemption and preſervation. Yea the more graces or benefits he hath
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:35801:29"/>received of him, the more will hee feare to diſpleaſe him.
<note place="margin">Thanks muſt bee Orall and reall alſo.</note> All that GOD re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, is a <hi>cordiall Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of His Grace and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: <hi>My ſonne, give mee thy heart Prov.</hi> 23.26. our <hi>whole Duty</hi> is ſummarily comprehended in theſe words: <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and love him with all thy ſtrength, and with all thy might; and thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelfe.</hi> By this, may wee know, whether we <hi>love God,</hi> if we <hi>love our neighbour:</hi> For how can he love God <hi>whom hee hath not ſeene,</hi> if he love not his brother <hi>whom he hath ſeene,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.20.</note> who as he had the Honour to bee ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:35801:30"/>
                     <hi>The diſciple whom Ieſus loved,</hi> ſo doth he ſeeme to have appropriated to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the preaching and teaching this doctrin <hi>(of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God and our neighbour)</hi> above all the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as may be ſeene by his Divine Epiſtles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will ſet him up</hi> (ſaith the Pſalme) <hi>becauſe hee hath knowne my Name:</hi> that is, becauſe he hath call'd upon me and worſhipped me: as may be collected out of the 76 <hi>Pſalme</hi> 1.2. <hi>In Iury is God knowne, his Name is great in Iſrael; at Salem is his Tabernacle:</hi> (which was the appointed place of his Worſhip.) If then we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to bee delivered and to be ſet up <hi>(out of Gun-ſhot)</hi> as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:35801:30"/>here is promiſed, we muſt not only love <hi>him,</hi> and our Neighbour <hi>for his ſake,</hi> but worſhip Him alſo <hi>in ſuch ſort</hi> as hee hath preſcribed in His moſt ſacred Word. Theſe <hi>Religious duties</hi> are neceſſarily required of all thoſe which expect the Comforts which this <hi>Pſalm</hi> exhibites. For, all the Aſſiſtance and Protection promiſed (from the firſt words throughout the Pſalme) have a connexion with this <hi>preſent clauſe: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath ſet his love up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me: becauſe he hath known my Name:</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">That is, to the utmoſt of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lically, not legally.</note> and a conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>reference</hi> thereto. So that whoſoever loves not God
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Zech.</hi> 7.12, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>perfectly,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.) nor worſhips him <hi>truly,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaves
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:35801:31"/>himſelfe, if he think hee dwels under the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the moſt High, or that he hath any part in the promiſes of Deliverance <hi>here ſpecified,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>proper</hi> only to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; who being aſſiſted with his holy Spirit, ſhall call upon him ſo effectually, and knocke at Heaven gates ſo powerfully, that he ſhall heare them and deliver them: yea and ſatisfie them with long life (which is more than <hi>Salomon</hi> deſired, when God gave him <hi>Carta vianca</hi>) and ſhew them his ſalvation; <hi>which is as much as any man can wiſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I confeſſe, Sickneſſe, <hi>Poverty,</hi> and all other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall <hi>Mortifications</hi> render
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:35801:31"/>men <hi>contemptible</hi> and <hi>deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable</hi> to the <hi>Wicked,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">N. B.</note> and make them <hi>undervalued</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Iames</hi> 2.2, <hi>to</hi> 8.</note> by ordinary Chriſtians, who paſſe their judgments of Men, accordingly as they waigh (after the <hi>Worlds</hi> opinion) in the balance of <hi>Honour, Reputation</hi> and <hi>Wealth:</hi> But the Child of GOD is promiſed here not only a <hi>Preſervative</hi> againſt all dangers (ſo farre and ſo long as God ſhall judge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for him) but alſo a <hi>Reſtorative,</hi> when hee hath beene afflicted and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. For if his enemies have markt him out <hi>(as their cuſtome is)</hi> in the time of his Humiliation, for one whom GOD lookt not after, nor car'd for: hee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:35801:32"/>hath a <hi>promiſe</hi> here to bee advanced to Honour, and (which is the height of all temporall Bleſſings) to be ſatisfied with <hi>long life:</hi> ſo that hee ſhall over-live his enemies and be honord by thoſe that deſpiſed him, <hi>when the hand of God was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let <hi>Ahaziah</hi> then ſend to <hi>Baalzebub,</hi> the God of <hi>Ekron,</hi> in the time of his ſickneſſe, to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſhall live or dye: Is it not becauſe there is no GOD in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> ſaith the LORD: 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1. Let gowtie <hi>Aſa</hi> truſt in his Phyſitians, 2 <hi>Chronicles</hi> 16. Let the ſuperſtitious <hi>Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> in his ſickneſſe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin</hi> by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:35801:32"/>vowing himſelfe to her: <hi>Quum nulla amplius in Medicis ſpes erat ſalutis, &amp; non magna</hi> (as he blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly ſaid) <hi>in Deo:</hi> Let them vainly truſt to the <hi>Oyle of the Lampe</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Dignus morte perit, qui mortua vivus ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. An experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts vaine confidence in Reliques, againſt the Plague.</note> of Saint <hi>Carlo Borromeo,</hi> the diſpenſation whereof <hi>I have ſeene with my eyes,</hi> and my Soule hath <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> to ſee ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple abuſed by more ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant <hi>Friers.</hi> In <hi>Iurea,</hi> the truſting to that <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,</hi> coſt the lives of the moſt part of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and <hi>Milan,</hi> (whence it was brought) hath <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered</hi> beyond beliefe, there having died <hi>in that ſtate,</hi> neere three hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſoules.</p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:35801:33"/>
                  <p>Not without cauſe, ſaid the Prophet, <hi>O bee thou my helpe in trouble, for vaine is the helpe of man, Pſalme</hi> 60.11. and <hi>Pſalme</hi> 77.1. <hi>In time of danger I will cry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, yea to God will I cry, and he ſhall hearken unto me.</hi> I deny not but <hi>Phyſicall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes,</hi> and <hi>Praecautiens</hi> may be uſed as <hi>ſecundary</hi> means: but they muſt be uſed <hi>with Prayer to God to bleſſe them:</hi> and our <hi>immediate Truſt</hi> muſt be <hi>wholly in him,</hi> and his protection. For, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord build the houſe, vaine is their labour that build it,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1.2. and therefore,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.7.</note> 
                     <hi>O Iſrael, truſt in the Lord, for with the Lord is Mercy, and with him is plenteous Redemption.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:35801:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> Againſt the whole <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of this Pſalme, and the maine <hi>ſcope</hi> thereof, there is an Objection not to be paſt over in ſilence. For whereas <hi>David</hi> here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth <hi>great matters</hi> to the godly, aſſuring them of the protection of God, and his Angels, and further, that <hi>with their eyes they ſhall ſee the Reward of the ungodly;</hi> Experience daily ſhewes the contrary; and hath ſo done ſince the beginning of the world. Innocent <hi>Abel</hi> loſt his life for ſerving <hi>God</hi> truely, and for Gods accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his ſervice: and our Saviour Epitomizing the Scriptures in this point, threatens the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them ſhall come all the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:35801:34"/>righteous bloud ſhed on the earth; from righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.35. The Church of GOD here on earth is therefore called <hi>Militant,</hi> becauſe it never hath peace, but perpetuall Warre, affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, tribulation, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the enemies thereof being mightie, viz. <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. Our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly commands all his Followers to <hi>take up his Croſſe:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Wicked moſt dand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Worlds lap.</note> and in the Book of Pſalmes we finde <hi>David</hi> often complaining of the Adverſities of the godly, and proſperity of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: In the 73. <hi>Pſal.</hi> he was ſhrewdly <hi>ſtartled</hi> at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of this point.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:35801:34"/>
                     <hi>My feete were almost gone: my ſteps well nigh ſlipt:</hi> And why? <hi>I was grieved at the wicked: I ſaw the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſuch proſperitie: for they are in no perill of death, in no misfortune, nor plagues as others are; but lusty and ſtrong, &amp;c.</hi> Contrarily, of the godly hee ſaith: <hi>Thou feedeſt them with bread of Teares,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 80.5. and (which is more) <hi>For thy ſake are we killed all the day long.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
                     </label> This <hi>difficulty</hi> is ſoone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, by diſtinguiſhing in God the qualities of a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and of a <hi>Iudge:</hi> to his <hi>Elect</hi> an indulgent <hi>Father:</hi> to the <hi>Reprobate</hi> a ſevere <hi>Iudge.</hi> A loving Father cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects his delinquent Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:35801:35"/>yet ceaſes not to care for them, but recomforts them when they amend: So deales God with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and is therefore ſtil'd the <hi>Shepheard of</hi> ISRAEL, and deſcrib'd, to have a <hi>Rod</hi> and <hi>Paſtorall ſtaffe:</hi> a <hi>Rod,</hi> to <hi>beat</hi> his <hi>wandring</hi> ſheep, a <hi>ſtaffe</hi> to <hi>keepe off</hi> the <hi>devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Wolfe.</hi> Yea, both theſe are not onely <hi>uſefull</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, but <hi>comfortable.</hi> Thy <hi>Rod</hi> and <hi>Staffe comfort me,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Prophet, Pſal.</hi> 23.4. and againe: It is
<note n="*" place="margin">O bleſſed Rod of God which doth ſo much good.</note> 
                     <hi>good</hi> for me, that I have beene <hi>in Trouble,</hi> that I may learne thy ſtatutes: Before I was <hi>troubled,</hi> I went <hi>wrong,</hi> but now I have kept thy word: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. The wicked (I grant) may inſult
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:35801:35"/>and triumph over the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when they ſee them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; and having their eyes ſwolne with fatneſſe, they may blaſpheme wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly and talke againſt the moſt High:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 73.</note> But <hi>in the ſame Pſalme,</hi> we read their doom <hi>Pſalme</hi> 17.18, 19. They are ſet in <hi>ſlippery places,</hi> caſt downe and deſtroyed, yea ſuddenly conſumed, and come to a fearefull end. This Myſterie <hi>David</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe underſtood not, till he went into the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> Then was hee grieved for the <hi>vengeance</hi> falne upon them,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ver.</hi> 20.21.</note> and adjudg'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for a <hi>foole</hi> and a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> in reflecting ſo much on their momentany Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:35801:36"/>
                  <p>Contrariwiſe, when the godly are <hi>chaſtiſed,</hi> it is done only to <hi>humble</hi> them: and the more they deject themſelves, the more will God erect them; putting them into the fire, not like <hi>baſe mettall,</hi> to be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but like pure <hi>Gold</hi> to be <hi>purg'd</hi> from the Droſſe of ſin. <hi>Many are the troubles of the Righteous,</hi> yet <hi>(at laſt)</hi> the Lord <hi>delivers them out of all;</hi> ſhould they live the age of <hi>Methuſalem,</hi> and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution all that while, what were <hi>thoſe yeares</hi> of <hi>Eternity,</hi> to which they aſpire? Let the <hi>godly and Religious</hi> then <hi>boldly rely on the Comforts of this Pſalme:</hi> for, if hee feare the Plague, it ſhall not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:35801:36"/>come nigh him; (<hi>that is,</hi> to <hi>harme him:</hi>) and if any <hi>other Affliction</hi> beſide him, it ſhall <hi>turne to his Good; in this, or a better life.</hi> For, we know, that <hi>all things work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together for the beſt, to them that love God;</hi> and the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of <hi>this preſent time</hi> (of what <hi>nature</hi> ſoever) are not worthy to be ballanc'd with the glory w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhall be revealed in us, <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.28, 18. Let us therefore (according to the exhortation of the Divine <hi>Apoſtle</hi>) be <hi>ſtedfaſt, and unmoveable,</hi> alwayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding <hi>in the Work of the Lord,</hi> foraſmuch as wee know,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58</note> that our labour <hi>is not in vaine in the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>Laus tibi Domine IESU.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="meditation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:37"/>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:35801:37"/>
                  <head>A MEDITATION on the Hiſtory of <hi>Agag,</hi> King of AMALEK.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1 Sam. 15. Ver. 32.33.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>And Agag came unto him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licately: and Agag ſaid, Surely the bitternes of death is paſt. And <hi>Samuel</hi> hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Agag</hi> in peeces before the Lord in Gilgal.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>THe <hi>comfort</hi> which our <hi>former Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> afforded us in the time of our greateſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:35801:38"/>
                     <hi>danger,</hi> hath need of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Temper or <hi>Corrective,</hi> leſt preſuming too much on the protection of the Almightie, we let ſlip our Anchor, and make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke in the <hi>Haven,</hi> after we have eſcaped a ſtorme in the <hi>maine Sea.</hi> The <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites</hi> at <hi>Ionah's</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, repented in ſackcloth and Aſhes: Which may be a <hi>Document</hi> to us, not to put off our ſackcloth too ſoone, leſt we relapſe into greater <hi>danger</hi> then we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly feared.</p>
                  <p>Security is a Cradle which rockes men into a ſpirituall lethargy out of which they ſeldome or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver awake, till the ſound of the laſt Trumpet call them
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:35801:38"/>to judgment. To prevent this fatall diſeaſe, it will be good for us to meditate a little on the Hiſtory of <hi>Agag,</hi> who was neereſt Deſtruction, when hee thought himſelfe moſt free from danger.</p>
                  <p>Hee had ſome reaſon to thinke himſelfe <hi>ſecure,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a <hi>Priſoner of War</hi> and therefore exempt from <hi>Death</hi> by the <hi>Law of Nations.</hi> He was a <hi>King,</hi> and therefore the more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged. He had beene ſpared by <hi>Saul,</hi> whoſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner he was, and who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a King, had <hi>poteſtatem vitae &amp; necis:</hi> yet, when he thought himſelfe ſafe, it was worſe with him then with the reſt of the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites,</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:35801:39"/>for they periſht on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the ſword in the treat of Battell, but he in coole bloud was <hi>hewed in peeces. Pejor eſt morte, mortis modus.</hi> This is an excellent mirror, wherein wee may contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the fraile condition of Mankinde, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that we are ſet in <hi>ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery places,</hi> and have no ſure footing on <hi>any ground</hi> here on earth: being ready <hi>to fall,</hi> when we ſeeme to our ſelves to <hi>ſtand ſureſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our preſent Meditation ſhall propoſe,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The <hi>Danger</hi> of this <hi>Lethargike</hi> diſeaſe of <hi>Seou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The <hi>Symptoms</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate it.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Remedies</hi> to prevent it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:35801:39"/>
                  <p>
                     <note n="I" place="margin">The dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eſtate of ſinfull Security.</note>The <hi>Danger</hi> may be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated by <hi>Examples,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Examples.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated by <hi>Reaſons,</hi> and conuinced by the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi> of Scriptures. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are they which can learne to be wiſe by others <hi>Folly,</hi> and avoid thoſe Rocks which have mind them. <hi>A gag</hi> is not alone, in ſaying, <hi>The bitterneſſe of death is past,</hi> when the <hi>ſweeteneſſe</hi> of the Hope wherewith he ſolac'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, was turn'd into <hi>Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe</hi> and <hi>Gall.</hi> Hee hath company inough of thoſe that thought as he ſaid, and fared no better than hee did. When the men of <hi>Laiſh</hi> were ſecure <hi>(as they ſuppoſed</hi>) the <hi>Danites</hi> ſmote them with the edge of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:35801:40"/>ſword, and burnt their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 18.27. <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> judg'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Extra fortunae aleam,</hi> to bee out of the reach of danger, when walking <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtically,</hi> in his Royall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, hee ſaid; <hi>Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for the Houſe of the kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of my Majeſtie?</hi> But while the word was in his mouth, he heard a voyce from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>Thy Kingdome is departed from thee, Dan.</hi> 4 30, 31. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.22.</note> his ſonne though hee knew all this, yet <hi>thought</hi> that nothing could ſhake him, when being guarded with a thouſand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:35801:40"/>his Princes, and carowſing with them in the ſacred Chalices of the <hi>Temple,</hi> he ſaw a Hand write on the Wall, which made his joynts to be looſed, and his Knees to ſmite one againſt the other: the loſſe of life and Kingdome being then denounced to him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. <hi>Siſera</hi> and <hi>Holofernes</hi> ſlept foundly; when <hi>Iael</hi> nailed the one to the Ground, and <hi>Iudith</hi> ſtruck off the others Head.</p>
                  <p>Nor is this Diſeaſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the wicked alone (whom wee have hitherto exemplifi'd) but <hi>Epidemik</hi> and common to all men: even to the Church
<note n="*" place="margin">Security, one of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall ſins.</note> and Children of GOD. The <hi>Iewes,</hi> Gods <hi>ancient People,</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:35801:41"/>were ſeldome deliverd from any great perill, but ſoone after they drew on themſelves, as great, or greater, by their <hi>ſupine Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,</hi> and preſumption of Gods mercy: as is cleere in the 78. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and the Booke of <hi>Iudges,</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. Yea <hi>David</hi> Himſelfe, a man after GODS owne heart, had a <hi>ſpice</hi> of this diſeaſe, as appeares in the 30. <hi>Pſalme, In my proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I ſaid, I ſhall never bee removed, thou Lord, of thy goodneſſe haſt made my Hill ſo ſtrong, Ver.</hi> 6. but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, in the next ver. he confeſſes, that the <hi>Lord hiding his face, he was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and then he cried to the Lord, and went to him right
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:35801:41"/>humbly,</hi> being neere death, or in great feare of it, as appeares by the <hi>verſes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent.</hi> Thus danger ever treads on the heeles of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, and oft trips them up. I will cloſe theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, with our Saviours Parable, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſis</hi> or Application there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being common to all men, The rich man there, ſung a <hi>Requiem</hi> to his ſoule, when immediately it was ſaid, <hi>Thou foole, this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee, ver.</hi> 20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="II" place="margin">Reaſons.</note>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> hereof are evident. For, when men <hi>feare leaſt,</hi> they provide leſt againſt danger. A Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is never more ſubject to <hi>Surprize,</hi> then when tis un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:35801:42"/>The <hi>Trojans</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended themſelves bravely ten yeares together, while the enemy encampt before the Citie; but when the <hi>Greeks</hi> diſcamping, faind a Retrait, and came upon them unawares, the Town was ſuddenly taken, that held out ſo long. A Poët deſcribing the overthrow of that famous City, the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſaith thus:</p>
                  <p>—<hi>Sic profanatis ſacris, Peritura Troja perdidit pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Deos.</hi> They loſt their GODS, before they loſt their Towne. Their <hi>Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> had been ſtolne from them, which argued their careleſſe ſecurity. In like manner, tis <hi>ſeldome</hi> ſeene,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:35801:42"/>that men run any great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of life, <hi>livelihood,</hi> or <hi>liberty,</hi> but they firſt looſe GOD by carnall ſecurity. <hi>David</hi> in the prementiond
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 30: <hi>ver.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Pſalme,</hi> intimates the cauſe of his <hi>Trouble, Feare,</hi> and <hi>Danger,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou didſt turne thy face from me:</hi> implying, that <hi>he had firſt turn'd aſide from God,</hi> in the time of proſperity, when hee had ſaid, <hi>I ſhall never be removed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſecond Reaſon, may bee drawne from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion of our corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Luſt and Concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, whereto as we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline <hi>ſtrongly,</hi> ſo the Devill tempts us hourely. Now ſenſuality hath never ſo much power over a man as
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:35801:43"/>in proſperitie, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring us ſecure, no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile if we fall into ſenſles ſtupidity, and never reflect on the <hi>bitterneſſe of Death.</hi> The <hi>Prophet</hi> relating here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, (<hi>Pſalm.</hi> 32.) compares <hi>ſuch</hi> to the <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Mule,</hi> which have no underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, whoſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Affliction fires out corruption.</note> mouths muſt bee holden with <hi>Bit</hi> and <hi>Bridle:</hi> that is, <hi>Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>Tribulation,</hi> which reſtraine men <hi>commonly</hi> from precipitating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſuch <hi>groſſe ſinnes</hi> as otherwiſe they were apt to fall into. <hi>Afflictio domat cupiditates, exerat fidem, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronat patientiam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The laſt reaſon is defect of underſtanding,
<note place="margin">Inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the common errour of the World; and the chiefe cauſe of all groſſe ſins and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors. <hi>See</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.14.</note> and want of ſound Iudgement
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:35801:43"/>in <hi>moſt men,</hi> who ſeldome looke further then <hi>the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and conſider not</hi> what may fall out hereafter. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes</hi> upbraiding the <hi>Athenians</hi> with Improvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and incircumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, preſented to them an <hi>innocent Foole,</hi> who being ſtruck on the <hi>one Cheek,</hi> laid his hand on the place where he had received the blow, and being ſmit <hi>on the other did the like:</hi> never uſing either of his hands to defend himſelfe from fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blowes. Such is the caſe of mankind: <hi>Ubi dolor, ibi digitus:</hi> Wee are ſo poſſeſt with worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or ſo beſotted with pleaſures, that we never think on Gods Iudgments
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:35801:44"/>but while they are <hi>preſent;</hi> and if we eſcape, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude (with <hi>Agag) The bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of death is past:</hi> not conſidering, that ſo long as we carry <hi>ſinne</hi> about us, we carry <hi>Nemeſin à tergo,</hi> Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſtill dogs us, and (without Repentance) will at laſt overtake us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="III" place="margin">Scripture Proofs.</note>
                     <hi>Scripture Authorities</hi> to confirme this point, are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to any that hath ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the <hi>Book of God,</hi> there being nothing more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, then exhortations to vigilancy, and dehortations from ſecurity. Yea the Prophets are therfore ſtil'd <hi>Watchmen,</hi> becauſe they are appointed to watch <hi>over us,</hi> that when we ſleepe in ſecurity (as the Diſciples
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:35801:44"/>did, at the inſtant when the <hi>Shepheard</hi> was to be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and the <hi>Sheepe</hi> to bee ſcatterd) they might ſound an Alarme in our eares, and rouze us to conſideration of our danger.</p>
                  <p>In the Greek <hi>Anthology,</hi> we reade of a Phyſitian, who having two <hi>Patients,</hi> the one <hi>Lunatike,</hi> the other <hi>Lethargike,</hi> lockt them up both in one <hi>Roome,</hi> when he that was <hi>frantick</hi> did ſo beat the <hi>Lethargik,</hi> that he kept him from ſleeping (by force) and ſo cur'd him: and (withall) ſo wearied himſelfe with beating, that he fell a ſleep, and recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red likewiſe. If we apply this to our ſelves, it may ſerve to ſhew us, what a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:35801:45"/>
                     <hi>perillous diſeaſe</hi> a Lethargy is, which requires <hi>blowes</hi> to cure it, the <hi>ſmart</hi> whereof we may feele, and beare the <hi>Markes,</hi> a long while after. If therefore after ſome great croſſe or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger over-paſt, our carnall luſts deſire to <hi>renew their acquaintance with us,</hi> the Vanities of the <hi>World</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure us, or the <hi>Devill</hi> would perſwade us to think, that the <hi>bitterneſſe of Death is paſt,</hi> yet, as we tender our owne <hi>ſoules,</hi> let us not give eare to thoſe <hi>charming temp tations,</hi> leaſt (with <hi>Agag</hi>) we be <hi>hewne in peeces,</hi> when we leaſt ſuſpect it. <hi>Nemo tam Divos habuit faventes, Craſtinum ut poſſit ſibi pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liceri:</hi> In our beſt health,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:35801:45"/>wee cannot promiſe to our ſelves <hi>a Day:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, can never ſay, <hi>the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe of death is paſt;</hi> ſince every <hi>Day,</hi> is a ſtep to Death; yea every <hi>Houre</hi> and <hi>Moment.</hi> Our bodies are but earthen Veſſels, which a ſmall knocke will breake: ſo that they who have eſcapt a <hi>furious plague,</hi> may dye of a <hi>ſmall Fever</hi> or <hi>ſurfet.</hi> Thus worldly dangers and diſaſters ſtill hover over our heads, and compaſſe us round: and therefore none can truely ſay, that the <hi>bitterneſſe of death is past,</hi> but thoſe only that are reconciled to God by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up Death in Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and exempted his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:35801:46"/>from its ſting and <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe.</hi> The danger of this <hi>ſpirituall Lethargie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great and <hi>impendent,</hi> let us conſider, what ſignes or <hi>Symptoms</hi> thereof may bee found in our corrupt Natures, that perceaving our owne perillous eſtate, wee may ſeeke to prevent it, by applying ſuch reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies as are proper and <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt marke or ſigne of this foule diſeaſe,
<note place="margin">Symptoms of ſecurity.</note> is a giddle and <hi>vertiginous</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; which is moſt viſibly ſeene in Reprobates, who <hi>runne madly after their owne wild luſts,</hi> and purſue their pleaſure with ſuch <hi>greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> as apparently ſhewes, they have no ſenſe nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:35801:46"/>of Death or Iudgement. Theſe kinde of men the Pſalmiſt paints <hi>in their colours, Pſalm.</hi> 59.5. they offend of <hi>malitious wickedneſſe,</hi> verſe 6. they <hi>runne to and fro,</hi> and about the Citie: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. They <hi>care not for God,</hi> nor <hi>once thinke of him.</hi> Theſe are entred into a <hi>Lethargie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in the head, and having loſt <hi>regimen intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus,</hi> whereby they might underſtand their <hi>owne dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> Being thus <hi>infatuated,</hi> they <hi>wilfully</hi> runne into <hi>all kind of wickedneſſe,</hi> and ſo falling into the <hi>Devils ſnares,</hi> are taken captive by him at <hi>his will,</hi> 2 <hi>Timothy</hi> 2.26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> A ſecond <hi>Symptome,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:35801:47"/>an inclination to ſecurity; is ſpirituall <hi>drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, ſaintneſſe</hi> and <hi>weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> in <hi>Gods</hi> ſervice. <hi>Spon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanea laſsitudo indicat mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum.</hi> This is ordinarily ſeene in the <hi>Vulgar ſort of Chriſtians,</hi> who are meere <hi>Nominals,</hi> and profeſſe Chriſtianity only for <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion.</hi> Sundry of theſe, as they do no hurt, (their <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior</hi> converſation being faire and unexceptionable) ſo they doe <hi>no good.</hi> They can <hi>ſay prayers,</hi> but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>pray,</hi> as wanting the <hi>Spirit
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Zech</hi> 12, 10</note> of Grace and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> They honour GOD with their <hi>lips,</hi> but their <hi>hearts</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Such learn Religion by Roto, not by Heart: having no regard of their owne ſoules, as appeared by their lewd lives.</note> are farre from him. They goe to <hi>Church,</hi> to <hi>ſleepe there:</hi> and heare
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:35801:47"/>Sermons; but with no <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> to the Doctrine, nor <hi>intention</hi> to doe thereafter. Theſe <hi>Carnall Goſpellers</hi> may ſee themſelves in the ordinary <hi>Pictures</hi> of <hi>Cain,</hi> and <hi>Abel:</hi> the ſmoke of <hi>Cains</hi> ſacrifice being pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>deſcending to the earth,</hi> but that of <hi>Abels, mounting towards Heaven,</hi> intimating, that <hi>Cain</hi> ſerv'd God <hi>dully, heavily</hi> and <hi>perfunctorily:</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> with <hi>Zeale, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> If we be thus <hi>qualified,</hi> wee may boldly approach the <hi>Throne of Grace:</hi> for, with <hi>ſuch ſacrifices</hi> God is well pleaſed.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, whether we <hi>bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatly armd</hi> againſt our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:35801:48"/>enemies, and well provided of <hi>Antidotes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſpirituall <hi>Diſeaſes.</hi> For if wee have laid by our <hi>Armes,</hi> tis an argument, that we feare nothing, and a <hi>ſhrewd ſigne</hi> that ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie begins to <hi>rocke us.</hi> If we have caſt away our <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatives,</hi> it argues a ſtrong preſumption of a ſound Conſtitution: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, yet, we may <hi>deceave our ſelves,</hi> as the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> did, who thought her ſelfe <hi>rich,</hi> and <hi>to want nothing,</hi> when ſhee was <hi>poore, blinde,</hi> and <hi>naked, Apoc.</hi> 3.17. Phyſitians ſay, <hi>Athletica conſtitutio pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſtat a morbo;</hi> and therefore let him that thinkes himſelfe ſo ſtrong
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:35801:48"/>that he needs no <hi>Antidote,</hi> know that he is neere fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into ſome deſperate diſeaſe. Our Spirituall Armes are the <hi>Shield of Faith, the Helmet of Hope, the Sword of the Spirit (Eph.</hi> 6.)
<note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of proofe.</note> and the <hi>Breſt plate</hi> of <hi>Charitie,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. which if we lay aſide, and <hi>unharneſſe</hi> our ſelves, (as he that <hi>returnes</hi> from War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare) wee lye open to our enemies (who ſometime make a <hi>Truce</hi> with us, but never firme <hi>Peace</hi> in this world) and therefore are in danger of a <hi>Surprize.</hi> Our preſervatives, are <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Repentance:</hi> which firſt, is a <hi>Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> an <hi>Ingredient</hi> that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into all <hi>ſpirituall Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines:</hi>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:35801:49"/>if wee bee ſlacke, <hi>therein,</hi> and pray not <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes</hi> with <hi>all manner</hi> of prayer and ſupplication of the ſpirit, it is a ſigne, this Lethargik diſeaſe is grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, it is expedient, to make a <hi>Synchroniſme,</hi> or compariſon of the Times, in which we have been in <hi>Adverſity,</hi> and <hi>Proſperity,</hi> and to obſerve, how wee have been <hi>affected</hi> therein. In time of <hi>danger,</hi> we look up to God, wee bemone our ſelves, confeſſe our ſinnes, profeſſe our peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, acknowledge Gods Iuſtice, implore his Mercy, proſtrating our ſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in faſting and weeping: Wee <hi>(then)</hi> are
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:35801:49"/>diligent in hearing Gods word, and meditating ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; frequent in works of Mercy to the poore and needy, willing to <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate,</hi> ready to <hi>diſtribute,</hi> as ſeeming deſirous <hi>(thereby)</hi> to <hi>lay up in ſtore for our ſelves a good foundation of happie eternitie,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19. Now let us examine our ſelves, whether in time of <hi>proſperity</hi> we have not <hi>coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> or <hi>relented</hi> in any of theſe ſpirituall duties, in which we were formerly ſo <hi>fervent</hi> and <hi>diligent:</hi> whether our <hi>Zeale</hi> be not <hi>lukewarme,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A memento for backſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</note> our <hi>Charitie fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen,</hi> our <hi>Devotion faint,</hi> our <hi>Prayers perfunctory,</hi> our ſervice of God onely <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall</hi> and <hi>ſuperficiall;</hi> and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:35801:50"/>laſtly, whether we ſay not in our hearts, <hi>O that Iſmael might live in thy ſight!</hi> that ſo we might entertaine our <hi>old Concubine Hagar</hi> (the <hi>luſts</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh</hi>) after <hi>Iſaac</hi> the childe of Promiſe is borne. If we find in our ſelves any ſuch <hi>Alteration,</hi> or <hi>diſinclination</hi> from pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous duties, we may aſſure our ſelves, that Satan ſeeks to lull us aſleepe in ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, we muſt <hi>exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerve,</hi> whether after deliverance from danger, wee have not omitted to glorifie our Deliverer, in imitation of that thankfull <hi>Samaritan, Luk.</hi> 17.15, 16. who being cured of his Leproſie by our Saviour,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:35801:50"/>
                     <hi>with a loud
<note n="*" place="margin">Compare Luk. 19.37.</note> voyce glorified God,</hi> and fell downe <hi>on his face</hi> at Chriſts <hi>feet,</hi> giving him thanks. When God ſpar'd <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> from the Plague, at the inſtance and interceſſion of <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24 17, 18.</note> the Prophet <hi>Gad</hi> commanded him to erect an <hi>Altar</hi> in the threſhing floore of <hi>Arau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> and to ſacrifice to the Lord: whence it appeares, that when we have recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved any bleſſings or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from God, he <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects,</hi> yea
<note n="*" place="margin">See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.14, 15.</note> 
                     <hi>commands,</hi> that we offer to him the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſticall ſacrifices of Praiſe and Thankes.</hi> Which, if with the nine <hi>Lepers, (Luk.</hi> 17.17.) wee faile to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, it is a ſigne that the Enemy of our Soules hath
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:35801:51"/>ſo ſtupified us with ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that we dare not be ſo brutiſh as to put in practiſe that damnable <hi>Italian</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, <hi>Fatto il voto, gabbato il ſanto:</hi> and conſequently that he intends our eternall ruine, by perſwading us to thinke, that the bitterneſſe of Death is paſt, and that God hath but <hi>one Arrow in his Quiver,</hi> which he hath ſhot <hi>over our heads</hi> only to affright us.</p>
                  <p>Having declar'd the <hi>ſymptomes</hi> of this ſinfull <hi>Lethargy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Remedies againſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</note> we ſhall now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe ſome <hi>Remedies</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. In healing whereof I will paſſe over <hi>thoſe</hi> that have the <hi>Grand Vertigo</hi> (formerly ſpecified,) and ſend them all, to the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:35801:51"/>of <hi>incurable mad men,</hi> as being given over to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate minde: for of ſuch <hi>deſperate ſinners,</hi> the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> (10. and 59.) are principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bee underſtood: yet the wilfull ſinner that hath a <hi>leſſe degree</hi> of the <hi>Vertigo,</hi> muſt not be given over <hi>pro deplorato,</hi> for though he be <hi>farre gone,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Vertigo eſt diminuta Epilepſia. <hi>Fernel:</hi>
                     </note> and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly <hi>infected,</hi> yet he may be <hi>recovered;</hi> as the <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall,</hi> being well pincht with Hunger, returnd home to his Father. They are <hi>bad Natures,</hi> that will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, when they are out of their way, till they <hi>ſmart ſoundlie</hi> for their Errours. Such, muſt have a <hi>Boaner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> to thunder into their deafe eares all the <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:35801:52"/>threatned in the book of <hi>God</hi> againſt obſtinat ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. <hi>Tophet</hi> muſt be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out unto them, flaming with fire and brimſton, <hi>God</hi> muſt bee repreſented to them <hi>as a revenging Iudge and conſuming fire.</hi> They muſt not heare a word of <hi>Peace,</hi> ſo long as the whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of <hi>Iezebel</hi> and her ſorceries are ſo many. They muſt bee threatned with Excommunication and exterminion out of the Aſſembly and ſociety of the faithfull: and laſtly, they muſt bee recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Prayers of the Church to Almighty God who muſt bee earneſtly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to open their eyes, molliſie their hearts, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:35801:52"/>give them a <hi>quicke ſenſe</hi> of their ſins, and of the danger whereinto they have caſt them. Theſe <hi>Remedies</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl'd, may (by the aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit) awake them out of that ſpirituall ſlumber, and reduce them to the fold of that <hi>good ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard,</hi> who rejoyceth more for finding one loſt ſheepe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 99. w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> went not aſtray When they are once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimd, <hi>ſalva res eſt:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 18.13.</note> For when they <hi>feele</hi> their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, they wil be induc'd to caſt it off (as too heavy) and addreſſe themſelves by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation and repentance, to our <hi>Lord, Ieſus;</hi> confeſſing their ſins, aggravating every circumſtance of them; and Imploring Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> GRACE and <hi>Mercy,</hi> till they obtain
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:35801:53"/>both, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.16. Laſtly, they will <hi>ſet their hearts</hi> to ſeeke God, and (with the Spouſe in <hi>Solomons ſong</hi>) never leave ſeeking their LORD and Saviour, till they have happily found him.</p>
                  <p>The next <hi>Symptome</hi> (ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in carnall Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers) was a dull ſtupidity and drowzineſſe in Gods ſervice, which though not ſo dangerous as the <hi>Vertigo</hi> praemention'd, yet ſhewes their diſpoſition to a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargy. And although their chiefe Errand to the Church, bee to <hi>gaze</hi> or <hi>ſleepe,</hi> or ſerve God <hi>pro for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> yet, as <hi>many</hi> followed Chriſt, more for Curioſity to ſee his Miracles, then
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:35801:53"/>for any devotion to His Doctrine, and yet (at laſt) <hi>ſome of them</hi> became His <hi>Diſciples:</hi> ſo there may be ſome hope conceav'd of theſe <hi>Superficialiſts,</hi> that if <hi>one Sermon</hi> rowze them not, <hi>another</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Therefore M. <hi>Latimer</hi> wiſht ſuch to come to Church, though they came a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</note> may; and that they may meet with ſuch a <hi>Chapter</hi> or ſuch a <hi>Pſalm;</hi> as may touch them <hi>to the quicke.</hi> Thus, <hi>one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> of Saint <hi>Peters,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted three thouſand,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41.</note> who came about him, to <hi>heare onely what hee would ſay:</hi> (whereas in theſe dayes, three <hi>thouſand Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> can ſcarce convert <hi>One.</hi>) Thus, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> comming to heare Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> at <hi>Milan,</hi> out of an impreſſion of his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:35801:54"/>was caught una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, and of one Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Manichee</hi> became the greateſt light of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that the Church en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyd ſince the Apoſtles times. Theſe <hi>faint</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall Christians</hi> muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and conſider, that God is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and will be worſhipt in Spirit and truth: <hi>In truth:</hi> that is, in <hi>ſincerity</hi> of heart, and not <hi>hypocritically,</hi> for <hi>faſhions</hi> ſake: <hi>In Spirit:</hi> that is, with <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Fervour:</hi> not <hi>coldly</hi> and <hi>drowzily. Awake</hi> then thou that <hi>ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt ſupinely,</hi> and <hi>dreame</hi> not
<note n="*" place="margin">Read Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. 7.6, 11 12, 13.</note> that God will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect thee or deliver thee from danger, if thou offer him the <hi>Sacrifice of fooles,</hi>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:35801:54"/>and demeane thy ſelfe ſo <hi>profanely</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Profaners of Gods Worſhip, encreaſe their owne condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29</note> and <hi>irreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi> in the houſe of Prayer, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1. What though <hi>Ahab</hi> purchaſd a temporall bleſſing with a <hi>formall ſhew and Vizor</hi> of Repentance? it profited not his Soule; and the <hi>Vengeance</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt him, fell heavie on his <hi>Poſterity.</hi> So may the <hi>cold Formaliſt,</hi> and <hi>profane Varlet</hi> proſper <hi>a while</hi> upon Earth; and though <hi>He</hi> goe to the grave in peace, <hi>his children</hi> may be <hi>hewd in peeces</hi> with Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, for <hi>thoſe ſinnes of his</hi> whereof he had <hi>no fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> Wherefore when thou ſeeſt the <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>Gods Iudgments gather,</hi> and ſome <hi>blacke Diſaſter</hi> threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:35801:55"/>thee for thy ſins, thou muſt imitate the Prophet <hi>Eliah,</hi> who when the ſtorme approcht, girt up his Loines and <hi>ranne</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ahab</hi> to <hi>Iezreel.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.45, 46.</note> If thou rowze thy ſelfe in that ſort, <hi>to runne the way of Gods Commandements,</hi> then maiſt thou ſafely ſhelter thy ſelfe under his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Eliah's</hi> Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Heaven in a <hi>fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> is an <hi>Emblem</hi> of that <hi>inflamed Zeale</hi> which muſt mount us to Heaven. <hi>The Kingdome</hi> of Heaven (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>ſuffers vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> and the <hi>Violent take it.</hi> Thus <hi>Iacob</hi> wreſtled with GOD for a bleſſing, and prevailed. <hi>Tis quoque fac ſimile.</hi> Doe thou ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:35801:55"/>thou <hi>dull drowzie Chriſtian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Such Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceans are but halfe baked, as Hoſea's cake was. Hoſe. 7.8. They ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter latitude in Religion then there is: ſo that they need not to bee zealous, nor make ſuch poſt-haſt to Heaven.</note> that ſerveſt God <hi>betwixt ſleeping and wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> and remember what befell <hi>Eutychus,</hi> who was taken up dead, for ſleeping at Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.9.</p>
                  <p>The third marke of this ſpirituall Lethargy, like a <hi>Scorpion,</hi> carries about her, both her <hi>Poyſon</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote.</hi> For when wee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceave our ſinnes of <hi>Omiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the <hi>dangerous Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele</hi> thereof; wee cannot but know, that the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation muſt needs bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to us. Seeing therefore that wee are in <hi>continuall Danger</hi> of our ſworne and deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the <hi>Devill</hi> and his
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:35801:56"/>
                     <hi>Angels;</hi> it concerns us to be <hi>armd at all points,</hi> and ſtil to ſtand upon our guard, leaſt being diſarmd, we be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſurprized.
<note place="margin">Gen. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> having armd 318. of his own Family, and aſſiſted with <hi>Aner, Eſhcol</hi> and <hi>Mamre</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame 4. Kings, whom he ſurpriſed by night, when queſtionles they were <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armd',</hi> and thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>ſecure.</hi> From this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive the firſt original of the <hi>order of Knight-hood,</hi> affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he Knighted <hi>Aner, Eſhcol</hi> and <hi>Mamre,</hi> for their good ſervice in that expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
<note place="margin">Originall of Knight-Hood,</note> However, we may thence conclude, that a handfull of men may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feate great Armies, by the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:35801:56"/>like ſtratagem. And ſeeing our ſpirituall enemies are innumerable of Devils, which are not only <hi>excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding potent,</hi> but <hi>ever vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant,</hi> and ful of <hi>ſtratagems,</hi> it concernes us to put on the whole <hi>Panoply,</hi> or Armour of <hi>God,</hi> and to be <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>vigilant</hi> like <hi>good Chriſtian Souldiers,</hi> reſiſting the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill with the ſword of the Spirit, and retorting his fiery <hi>Darts</hi> with the <hi>ſhield of Faith.</hi> The ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may induce us likewiſe to carry about us ſtill our ſpirituall Antidotes: for, as long as wee live, wee ſhall have need of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Penitence,</hi> which are the <hi>Cordials of the Soule.</hi> Wee came ſoule-ſicke into this
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:35801:57"/>World, of <hi>Originall ſinne,</hi> which being daily reen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc'd with <hi>Actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,</hi> will in <hi>time</hi> grow to a <hi>Pestilentiall Diſeaſe,</hi> and bring us to utter Perdition, if wee take not that Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, which God the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian of our ſoules hath preſcrib'd in his <hi>Divine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatory,</hi> beſeeching him daily on our bended knees to <hi>waſh</hi> and <hi>purge</hi> us, in the <hi>ſacred bloud</hi> of his onely Sonne and our only Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
                  <p>But thou wilt ſay, thou art of a temperate diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and findeſt thy ſelfe <hi>ſo well,</hi> as that thou haſt no need of <hi>Phyſicke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Be not deceav'd: <hi>Parum distat ab agroto, qui tantum
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:35801:57"/>ſanus est:</hi> Hee is <hi>neere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſicke,</hi> that is <hi>but well. Strength</hi> and <hi>Vigour</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd likewiſe, which are oft wanting in thoſe that <hi>feele not</hi> their owne <hi>Indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi> Againe, there are many ſecret <hi>diſeaſes</hi> of the Soule which thou ſeeſt not, as <hi>Selfe-love, ſpirituall pride, vaine thoughts, ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling inordinate-deſires, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable
<note n="*" place="margin">Charitie ever inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things favourably.</note> Conceits</hi> and the <hi>like,</hi> which are ſo much the more dangerous to bee cured, being ſo difficultly diſcern'd. Diſtruſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy <hi>owne Iudgement</hi> of thy ſelfe, remembring that, <hi>Prudentiae mater eſt diffiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Diffidence</hi> is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Prudence.</hi> For if thou examine thy life by
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:35801:58"/>the Rule of GODS Law, thou wilt finde thy ſoule full of a ſpirituall Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which nothing can cure, but the bleeding wounds of the immaculate <hi>Lambe of God, which taketh away all the ſinnes of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> note of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to that Lethargik diſeaſe, was the want of <hi>ſelfe-examination,</hi> viz. how we ſtood affected to holy <hi>duties</hi> in times of adverſitie and Proſperity, reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If then wee feele the <hi>Pulſe of our Soules</hi> to beate more <hi>faintly</hi> and <hi>weakely</hi> in our proſperous and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing eſtate, then it did when we were in Trouble or Danger, it is high time
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:35801:58"/>to looke to our ſelves, leſt we fall into a Lethargy. For as the leſt <hi>Declination</hi> of the Sunne from the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian,</hi> though inſenſible at the <hi>beginning,</hi> ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes, till the Sunne bee <hi>ſet:</hi> ſo the leſt <hi>relenting</hi> in the zealous
<note n="*" place="margin">M. Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer being asked, why there was ſo much prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and ſo little pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ignis: there wants fire, (viz. of Zeale.</note> practice of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> will in ſhort time prove a <hi>Retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation;</hi> which will caſt us mainly backward, and take quite from us, in the end, the light and Comfort of the <hi>Sunne of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are few men, that after they have ſung <hi>Te Deum,</hi> for any great Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, will ſeriouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member or thinke upon <hi>Miſerere mei Deus;</hi> preſent
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:35801:59"/>Proſperitie making them ſecure of future Danger, as if they needed not to pray, <hi>Leade us not into Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They have a Cuſtome in <hi>Italy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">[A relation of the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Revels and Baccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, the week before Lent.]</note> of putting out the <hi>Quaranta hore,</hi> (as they terme it) in the principall Churches, in the laſt week of <hi>Carneval,</hi> when <hi>Feast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Dicing, Dancing,</hi> and <hi>Masking,</hi> with all ſorts of licentious revelling, is <hi>ſhamefully priviledg'd</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. During thoſe <hi>fortie houres,</hi> they which have any Devotion, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the hearing of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, faſting and praying for the Remiſſion of their owne ſinnes and of thoſe that ſinne <hi>in that time of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:35801:59"/>exceſſe and looſeneſſe;</hi> which was the <hi>beſt peece of Pietie that I obſerved</hi> in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church.
<note place="margin">Weakneſſe of Faith, is (in degree) Want of Faith.</note> When we finde therefore a weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Faith, a <hi>faintneſſe</hi> in our Devotions, cold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to God and good men, fewer Teares ſhed for ſinne then <hi>formerly,</hi> leſſe remorſe of Conſcience and dread of Gods Iudgments, we may well ſuſpect in our ſelves a <hi>carnall</hi> and <hi>Carne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall Securitie,</hi> which by all pious meanes wee muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to prevent.</p>
                  <p>Howbeit, in this <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chroniſme</hi> or Collation of the times of our Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Proſperity, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not <hi>in all points</hi> the ſame ſpirituall exerciſes
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:35801:60"/>
                     <hi>without Variation,</hi> (as if there were no difference betwixt <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> and <hi>Good-Friday,</hi>) but a <hi>conſtant Tenour of ſerving God, all the dayes of our life,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>intermiſſion</hi> or <hi>remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>the eſſentiall duties</hi> of <hi>Religion:</hi> that, as in <hi>Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> we call'd on him for deliverance, ſo <hi>being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd,</hi> we forget not to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie his Divine Majeſty, as he hath
<note n="*" place="margin">See Pſal. 50. ver. 15. and 23.</note> commanded us: having ever a watchfull eye to our ſelves, that our Zeale to his ſervice relent not, nor our Charity to our neighbour wax
<note n="*" place="margin">Coldneſſe is a Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of death.</note> 
                     <hi>cold;</hi> and learning of holy <hi>Iob (ch.</hi> 9.) <hi>to feare all our workes,</hi> as knowing, that wee are to <hi>worke out our ſalvation,</hi> &amp;c. as wee are taught,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> which
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:35801:60"/>is not to bee underſtood, that we are to bee ſo feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as to doubt <hi>of the end; [if we continue in our faith,]</hi> but to be ſo carefull, and <hi>punctually circumſpect,</hi> as to omit no <hi>means</hi> thereto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducent.</p>
                  <p>The laſt ſigne, indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a propenſion in our ſoules to carnall ſecurity, was the Omiſſion of the <hi>Spirituall Sacrifices,</hi> of Praiſe and Thanks, after any bleſſing, comfort, or deliverance receaved from God. To <hi>remedie</hi> this, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires only an <hi>inſpection</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Booke of GOD, where wee ſhall finde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Precedents,</hi> ſeconded with moſt gracious promiſes,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:35801:61"/>exciting and even enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing us, to that heavenly exerciſe of glorifying <hi>God</hi> for all his <hi>Mercies. Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> doth preach to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and mainly preſſe on their Soules and Conſciences, two chiefe <hi>Doctrinall Points:</hi> viz. <hi>Obedience;</hi> and <hi>Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</hi> This was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend <hi>Patriarchs</hi> Practiſe, who never receav'd any bleſſing,
<note place="margin">The ancient practiſe of Piety by Geds true ſervants; worthy our imitation.</note> but <hi>immediately</hi> wee reade of an <hi>Altar</hi> by them erected: yea, if they found but <hi>Water for their Cattell,</hi> they gave to the <hi>Wells</hi> they had digged, <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant Names,</hi> expreſſing their <hi>Gratitude.</hi> The <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> deliverance at the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> produced the Song of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:35801:61"/>
                     <hi>Moſes.</hi> The Victory of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rak,</hi> the Song of <hi>Debora.</hi> The birth of <hi>Samuel,</hi> the Song of <hi>Hanna.</hi> The birth of the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> the Song of <hi>Zachary,</hi> and the <hi>Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation</hi> of our Saviours <hi>Nativity;</hi> the Bleſſed <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins Magnificat.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> hath left us on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeven <hi>penitentiall Pſalms,</hi> but his <hi>Euchariſticall pſalms</hi> of <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> are very numerous: not omitting to compoſe an Hymne of praiſe, for every <hi>ſignall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> that hee receaved at the hands of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Motives</hi> and <hi>Reaſons,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling yea compelling us to the performance of this duty, are many.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, among <hi>Ethniks,</hi>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:35801:62"/>and meere Morall men, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude</hi> is reputed the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> of Vices: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate perſons branded with the greateſt infamy. <hi>Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum dixeris, omnia dixeris.</hi> It is a violation of <hi>naturall Iuſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Partem benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cij reddidit, qui gratias de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit:</hi> He hath <hi>in part requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> a benefit, <hi>that returnes thankes.</hi> The Prophets de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was, <hi>Quid retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am?</hi> arguing, <hi>that ſome kinde of retribution was due to God</hi> for his bleſſings, <hi>Ex aequo &amp; bono:</hi> the neglect whereof, muſt needs bee adjudg'd a violation of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Equity.
<note place="margin">Gratitude a due debt.</note> 
                     <hi>Doe yee thus requite the Lord, ye Fooles?</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>See Deut.</hi> 32.6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:35801:62"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, Gratitude for <hi>Mercies receav'd,</hi> is the next way to purchaſe <hi>more</hi> from God: as the ſervant in the <hi>Parable,</hi> that improved the <hi>pound</hi> left with him by his Maſter, was made Ruler over <hi>tenne Cities, Luke</hi> 19, 16.17.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, whoſoever is <hi>truely thankfull</hi> to God, will endeavour to expreſſe his gratitude by <hi>Obedience,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending it to the whole courſe <hi>of his life,</hi> and to <hi>all the divine Commandements:</hi> not taking <hi>liberty</hi> in <hi>any one ſinne,</hi> but <hi>ſtriving</hi> to <hi>avoid all:</hi> nor omitting <hi>any Duty of Piety or Charity,</hi> but <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The Law may bee kept ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, though not fulfilld ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly.</note> performing <hi>all;</hi> like <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, who walked in all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:35801:63"/>and Ordinances of the Lord, unblameably, Luk.</hi> 1.6. As God never ceaſeth to beſtow his bleſſings on us, ſo ſhould wee <hi>inceſſantly</hi> ſerve, laud and magnifie him, all our days. In which <hi>heavenly exerciſes,</hi> if wee continue, conſtant, faithfull <hi>to death,</hi> wee ſhall receave a Crowne of Life, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.10.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, this <hi>holy Duty,</hi> is full of <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and a ſingular ſolace to the religious ſoule. <hi>O praiſe the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>for it is a good thing to
<note n="*" place="margin">Sing Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids Pſalms with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids ſpirit.</note> ſing praiſes to Our God,</hi> yea, <hi>a joyfull and pleaſant thing, to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Pſalm.</hi> 147.1. If we delight in this heavenly
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:35801:63"/>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Singing of Pſalmes to Gods glory.</note> 
                     <hi>Melodie,</hi> and <hi>ſoule-ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Harmonie,</hi> it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible we ſhould ever forget God. Therefore it is an <hi>Antidote</hi> of Soveraigne vertue againſt worldly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, the celebration of GODS Name, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to our memory the <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>diſaſters</hi> that we have paſt, (<hi>Pſalm.</hi> 54.6, 7.) and thoſe ſins of ours likewiſe that occaſioned them. The conſideration whereof may deterre us from <hi>ſinning,</hi> and teach us to <hi>ſtand in awe</hi> of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.4. leſt by committing <hi>new ſinnes,</hi> wee pull on our Heads <hi>new puniſhments:</hi> according to that <hi>terrible Commination of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:35801:64"/>God: Deut.</hi> 32.23. <hi>I will heape miſchiefes on them: I will ſpend mine Arrowes upon them:</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> 42. <hi>I will make mine Arrowes drunke with the bloud of the ſlaine, &amp;c.</hi> Let us therfore (<hi>as Moſes</hi> there adviſeth, <hi>ver.</hi> 46.) <hi>ſet our hearts</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Hardneſſe of heart, the cauſe of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Mark. 6.52. compard with, 2 Chr. 12.14</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>all theſe words,</hi> leſt after we have eſcapt the <hi>ſword of Saul,</hi> we be <hi>hew'd in peeces by Samuel.</hi> All <hi>relapſes into ſinne</hi> or <hi>ſickeneſſe,</hi> are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme perillous. <hi>Recidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va pejor Radice.</hi> Recidiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aggravates the crime, and makës the <hi>latter end</hi> worſe than the <hi>beginning:</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> teſtifies: (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20.) who reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles <hi>ſuch Delinquents</hi> to <hi>dogges</hi> and <hi>hogges:</hi> ver. 22.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:35801:64"/>Wherefore, let us not <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke to anger</hi> our heavenly <hi>Father,</hi> our gracious <hi>Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and ſweet <hi>comforter. Sinne no more</hi> (ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.14.) <hi>leaſt a worſe thing befall thee:</hi> that is; ſinne no more <hi>wilfullie:</hi> doe what thou canſt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it. Shun whatſoever hath any tincture of ſinne. Deteſt it, as the bane of thy ſoule,
<note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 16.38.</note> and abhorre thy ſelfe for it. Deſire to forbeare <hi>all ſinne,</hi> and that <hi>deſire</hi> ſhall exempt thee from the <hi>Guilt</hi> or <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi> Turne <hi>Hagar</hi> out of doores. Crucifie the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> with the <hi>Affections</hi> and <hi>luſts.</hi> Cruſh the <hi>Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice</hi> in the ſhell. <hi>Non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent peccata praeterita</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:35801:65"/>Saint <hi>Auguſtine) Si non placent praeſentia.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Sins paſt cannot harme us, if ſinnes preſent doe not pleaſe us. Be vigilant therefore, and keep an eye upon thy ſelfe, and all thy actions, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. Make a covenant with thine <hi>eyes;</hi> and ſet a <hi>ſtrict watch</hi> on thy <hi>lips;</hi> that thou offend not. Let <hi>Gods</hi> Law
<note n="*" place="margin">Qui diligit legem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligrt Regem.</note> and <hi>Word</hi> be a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to thy <hi>feet,</hi> by which thou maiſt order thy <hi>ſteps:</hi> then, if thou <hi>ſlide,</hi> thou ſhalt not fall: and if thou fall <hi>by infirmitie, Dominus ſupponet manum,</hi> the Lord Ieſus ſhall raiſe thee by his Power, and not
<note n="*" place="margin">See Iſaiah 41.10.</note> permit thee to be attempted <hi>above thy ſtrength.</hi> He is <hi>full of compaſſion,</hi> and will not
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:35801:65"/>deale with us <hi>after our ſins,</hi> nor reward us <hi>according to our Wickedneſſe;</hi> for hee knowes <hi>whereof wee are made,</hi> and remembers, that we are but <hi>Duſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Est piger ad poenas Iehova, ad praemiavelox;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dolet, quoties cogitur eſſe ferox.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Multa metu poenae, poenâ qui pauca coercet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et jacit invitâ fulmina rara manu.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Qui cum triſte aliquid ſtatuit, flt triſtis &amp; ipſe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> fere poenam ſumere, poena ſua eſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Gods bleſſings are more rife then's Maledictions:</l>
                     <l>He frets when he is forc'd to plague the Times;</l>
                     <l>Chooſing affrightments, rather than Afflictions,</l>
                     <l>Rarely he thunder-ſtrikes the greateſt crimes:</l>
                     <l>When he reſolves to ſtrike, he doth condole:</l>
                     <l>And when he ſtrikes, it grieves his very Soule.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Let us then wholly fixe our mindes on God, and embrace the divine Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of our bleſſed LORD and Redeemer: <hi>Watch and pray, that yee enter not into
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:35801:66"/>Temptation.
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.42.46.</note> Watch, for yee know not in what houre your Lord commeth. Bleſſed is that faithfull and wiſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, whom his Lord when he comes, ſhall finde ſo doing.</hi> But, <hi>if wee ſay in our hearts</hi> (with the <hi>evill ſervant,</hi> (<hi>Mat.</hi> 24.48.) <hi>Our Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes his comming,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>abandon our ſelves to all exceſſe of ſinning,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing our <hi>unſanctified af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> and <hi>extravagant lusts</hi> in all <hi>ſecurity,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> will come upon us <hi>in a Day</hi> when we <hi>looke not for him, and cut us in peeces, as Agag, when he leſt expected it.</hi> Let us remember, there is <hi>Dies &amp; Deus ultionis,</hi> a day and a God of Vengeance: that we muſt <hi>ſhortly</hi> appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:35801:66"/>His dreadfull Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, who is a <hi>Iudge,</hi> for wiſedome, infallible; for Iuſtice, inflexible. Behold, <hi>death</hi> is at <hi>our doores,</hi> and <hi>Iudgement hovers over our Heads,</hi> we cannot therefore <hi>conclude,</hi> that the <hi>bitterneſſe of death is paſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If therefore wee have any
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Taſte</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> any <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> any <hi>Impreſſion</hi> of <hi>Eternitie;</hi> any <hi>reſentment</hi> of ſinne (which raignes <hi>every where,</hi> to the ſubverſion of <hi>States,</hi> and deſtruction of <hi>Soules</hi>) let our converſation be <hi>honeſt, modeſt, ſober, pure,</hi> and <hi>holy,</hi> as becomes the <hi>Children of God,</hi> that wee may ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove to our ſelves, (by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendment
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:35801:67"/>of life) <hi>this grievous viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that the bleſſed <hi>Angels</hi> in Heaven may <hi>rejoyce</hi> at our converſion, and our Mercifull Father bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to continue to us His gracious protection. For, the <hi>Angell</hi> of the <hi>Lord, the volant miniſter of his Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> being ſtill abroad with his ſword <hi>drawne</hi> (as appeares
<note n="*" place="margin">[This was written in the time of the great plague in Italy and Savoy.]</note> by thoſe <hi>horrid ſpectacles</hi> of Mortality, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where viſible) it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes us <hi>All</hi> to <hi>humble our ſelves under the mighty hand of God.</hi> And as in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, wee may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly ſay, <hi>The bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death is paſt:</hi> much leſſe, in this time of Peſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and tribulation, ought we to <hi>ſleep in ſecuritie:</hi> leſt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:35801:67"/>wee be worthily <hi>branded</hi> with that <hi>ſtigmaticall Mark</hi> which is ſet upon <hi>Ahaz:</hi> (2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.22.) <hi>This is that King Ahaz:</hi> What had he done, that the Spirit of the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhould point at him with his finger, in that ſort, <hi>above all the reſt of the Kings of Iſrael and Iudah?</hi> the reaſon is there rendred: <hi>In the time of his diſtreſſe hee treſpaſſed yet more against the Lord.</hi> This is that King <hi>Ahaz. Theſe things</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) are <hi>Examples, for us</hi> to reflect on: and are <hi>written for our admonition,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11.</note> upon whom the ends of the World are come.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:68"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:68"/>
                  <p>AN ESSAY, OF FRIENDSHIP. VVritten, by a Noble <hi>GENTLE-MAN,</hi> DECEASED. And now, Reviſed, and Illuſtrated.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 PET. 1.22. and 3, 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>See that yee love one another, with a pure heart, fervently.</p>
                     <p>Having a good Conſcience, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they ſpeake evill of you, as of evill doers, they may be aſhamed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Amor Dei, amorem proximi generat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Badger,</hi> for <hi>H. Moſley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Princes Armes, in S. Pauls Church-Yard. 1640.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="essay">
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:69"/>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:35801:69"/>
                  <head>AN ESSAY, <hi>of Friendſhip.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of the World, <hi>MAN</hi> is the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent piece: and there is no particular Man, but in his <hi>Eſſence</hi> and <hi>nature</hi> is far more excellent then the Frame of all the reſt of the World. But, that man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men is moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, that can adde to his own Eſſence, <hi>another</hi> of equall worth.</p>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:35801:70"/>
                  <p>For, as wee hold him richer, that hath a pound of Gold, then he that hath ſo much Silver, and if a man did enjoy all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and the full power over all the world, ſo that he might juſtly call all the World, <hi>his own;</hi> we ſhould juſtly thinke <hi>this Man</hi> rich for poſſeſſing ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious things: yet, ſince there is ſomwhat that is of more Excellence then all the World, which is <hi>Man,</hi> he that fully injoyes <hi>a man,</hi> is richer than hee that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes <hi>all the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To enjoy a man, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have a <hi>Slave</hi> or <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant:</hi> of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> gives a man power over him for <hi>Feare:</hi> and the <hi>ſecond,</hi> for
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:35801:70"/>
                     <hi>Reward.</hi> And yet, the power that a man hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver either of theſe, is not over the man, but over the Body of the Man. For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare of puniſhment can tie a ſlave from <hi>diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient thoughts,</hi> nor hope of reward oblige a ſervant to perfect Obedience in his <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Will:</hi> becauſe neither thoſe offences can be puniſhed, nor thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts rewarded which are impoſſible to be knowne.</p>
                  <p>Hee hath onely obtaind this perfection of <hi>adding to his eſſence,</hi> who <hi>enjoyes a Friend,</hi> and hath gaind <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power</hi> over the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of another man. So that by the order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the World, a man
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:35801:71"/>
                     <hi>is really
<note n="*" place="margin">Siracides: 6.15.</note> richer</hi> and happier that hath a firme <hi>Friend,</hi> then hee that enjoyes all things elſe that the World can afford him.</p>
                  <p>But as a <hi>Lute</hi> muſt have the <hi>Wood</hi> well ſeaſond,
<note place="margin">The chiefe ground of our Love, ought to be Gods Image in men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in goodnes and godlineſſe: which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone may juſtly draw our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and the <hi>Frame</hi> joynd together, and perfected, before it have ſtrings put to it, and before it can make the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it ſelfe was made: So a man muſt have his <hi>Affections ſeaſond, his Paſſions temperd,</hi> and <hi>all himſelfe</hi> perfected with <hi>Vertue,</hi> before he is capable of the fulneſſe of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, which is receiv'd by perfect friendſhip.</p>
                  <p>The perfection of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, conſiſts in a ſtrong confederation, and an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:35801:71"/>Union between mens deſires and affections: So that whatſoever <hi>one</hi> deſires and affects, is equally affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and deſir'd by the <hi>Other.</hi> This <hi>Union</hi> can be betweene none but <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous</hi> men.
<note place="margin">Novicious perſon can be a perfect friend. Yet, the beſt have very many infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities (I am. 3.2.) which how they are to bee borne with; See Rom. 15 1, 2, 3.</note> For the <hi>Generall way of vertue is but One,</hi> in which al men agree, which travell out the Iourney of their life in this way: But <hi>there are infinite wayes of vice,</hi> which differ and diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as much one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in particular, as they doe in generall, from Vertue.</p>
                  <p>Friendſhip is indeed it ſelfe a vertue, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteſt, or rather the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and combination of all other Vertues: and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:35801:72"/>as it is a vertue, ſo it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind by induſtry. No men are borne friends. Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and thoſe between whom there is a neere con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitie, are borne with a <hi>greater diſpoſition</hi> to it, then <hi>ſtrangers:</hi> But that which makes a friendſhip, is <hi>Converſation:</hi> where firſt, there is a mutuall liking of one anothers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, becauſe they like what one another ſaith, or doth: and afterwards, continuance of converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and mutuall <hi>kindneſſe,</hi> and <hi>perpetuity</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">True A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, and permanent.</note> of agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bring things to that paſſe, that as at firſt, the men were liked for what they ſaid or did, ſo at laſt, the ſpeeches and Actions
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:35801:72"/>ſhall be liked, becauſe they are ſpoken or done by theſe men.</p>
                  <p>Out of this,
<note place="margin">
                        <p>There are 3. degrees in Love, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Beloved.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Defire of conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, or Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: which is ultimus actus amoris</p>
                     </note> there grows a deſire of <hi>imitating one another:</hi> and a deſire of putting thoſe things in practiſe themſelves, which they did ſo well like in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, till at laſt they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as it were <hi>two peeces cut out of one cloath.</hi> And as they grow in likeneſſe of diſpoſition, they muſt neceſſarily increaſe in friendſhip. For, that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Diſcretion which whilſt it was a ſtranger to them, <hi>pleaſd them ſo well,</hi> muſt needs much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light them, when they finde, that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly acquainted with it,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:35801:73"/>in their owne Practiſe.
<note place="margin">Friendſhip, a ſacred Bond and fraternall League; the Violation whereof, is hainous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety: A wound from a friend, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wound.</note> And in Concluſion, the Men will grow to bee but <hi>One man,</hi> and will eſteem themſelves ſo; and each friend will deſire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring the <hi>ſame things</hi> to paſſe, and with the <hi>ſame "Induſtrie,</hi> for his friend, as for himſelfe, and will bee <hi>equallie care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> for his <hi>Friends Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Eſtate, Life,</hi> and <hi>Contentment,</hi> as of his <hi>owne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When it comes to this, it is <hi>Friendſhip.</hi> All the reſt, is but <hi>familiar acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> and <hi>Well-wiſhing,</hi> and a <hi>good opinion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe, the Generall and <hi>Poſitive Rule</hi> of all thoſe things which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:35801:73"/>friends, as they ſtand in mutuall Relation one towards another, to bee, that in every Occaſion that is offerd a friend, to doe or ſay any thing <hi>as a friend,</hi> hee ought <hi>in Reaſon</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">For, a true friend is to be reputed a ſecond Selfe</note> to examine what he ought to doe or ſay, <hi>if it were his owne caſe;</hi> and juſt ſo, and no otherwiſe, he ought to doe and ſpeake concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his friend.</p>
                  <p>Out of this Generall diſcourſe we may grow to particular <hi>concluſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, ſince a <hi>Friend</hi> is more precious then all things in the World that a man can poſſeſſe <hi>beſides,</hi> a man ought to value more his <hi>Friend,</hi> then either his eſtate or <hi>preferment,</hi> or any
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:35801:74"/>other
<note n="*" place="margin">Hence it followes, that baſe Lucianiſts, complotting by Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantike practiſes, to rob a man of his true friend, are the moſt perillou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; pernicious Theeves in the World. See Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of them: Pro. c. 6. v. 16, 19. and Pro. 16.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Worldly</hi> things that he can pretend to.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, ſince one friend is the <hi>Eſſentiall part</hi> of the other, and two friends are united in one <hi>individuall eſſence</hi> of frind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, if this eſſence be once diſſolv'd by the <hi>utter diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> of their friendſhip, I hold it in the courſe of Nature as poſſible a thing for a ſoule to returne to a body that it hath forſaken and informe it againe; as for a perfect friendſhippe once broken to be reſtor'd to his former Perfection. And if at any time ſuch a thing happen, I ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme it a miracle. The impoſſibility of recovery of ſo precious a Iewell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:35801:74"/>once loſt, is another Argument why a Man that is once ſo happie as to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, ſhould be
<note n="*" place="margin">Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, is fine but brittle ſtuffe: and (in theſe dayes a very caſuall commodity: defeazible, on light oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and ſiniſter ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of Viperous Tongues, Mat. 24.12.</note> carefull to preſerve it. And ſince mens affections which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were different, are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and <hi>made one</hi> by friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, a man ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, what <hi>hee would</hi> expect from his friend, <hi>in ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch caſes,</hi> and <hi>juſt ſo</hi> hee ought to doe to him.</p>
                  <p>And on the contrary, he ought to conſider what he would do to his friend, upon ſuch and ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and juſt ſo he ought to expect from him. They are diſſemblers, that ſay <hi>they love any man better than themſelves,</hi> and becauſe they want the Truth of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:35801:75"/>friendſhip, they guild over the <hi>meaneſt of their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> with ſuch Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and make them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare more glorious then true friendſhip it ſelfe. He hath attaind the <hi>height of friendſhip</hi> who loves ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>equally to himſelfe:</hi> and friendſhip is ſo <hi>indiviſible a thing,</hi> that hee that <hi>loves not ſo,</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a falſe friend is thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by Siracides: If he have need of thee, hee will deceive thee, and ſmile upon thee, and put thee in hope: hee will ſpeake thee faire, and ſay, What wanteſt thou? And he will ſhame thee by his meates, and at laſt he will laugh thee to ſcorne, &amp;c. Eccl. 13.6, 7. Compare Prov. 23.6.7, 8. and Eccl. 18.18. and there will reſult the true Character of a cheating Laban, and churliſh Nabal. D.L.</note> is not worthy of the Name of a <hi>True Friend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Since then a man ought to love his friend, <hi>in the ſame degree</hi> that hee loves
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:35801:75"/>himſelfe, then is required betweene friends ſuch an Equality of Worth and Merit, that one Friend muſt in all congruity of Reaſon, equally deſerve to bee loved as the other; not in that opinion which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men have of them (for that is without them, and doth not concerne them) but in the opinion which they have one of another.</p>
                  <p>For, the reaſon, why a man loves his friend as well as himſelfe, is becauſe he aſſuredly beleeves, that his <hi>Friends Abilities</hi> are both as great, and as much his owne, as thoſe which he hath himſelfe; and that he can imagine no Danger
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:35801:76"/>or Inconvenience that hee would undergoe to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his owne content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that his friend would not with the ſame willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe put himſelf upon, for the ſame end. Neither is an Equality of Birth and Nobilitie to be required. For, (as I ſaid before) no men are borne friends, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Friendſhip between Men, as they are either <hi>Kings, Lords,</hi> or <hi>Beggers,</hi> but as they are <hi>Men.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is a juſt equality of <hi>Age</hi> neceſſary: though it bee very convenient that their yeares doe not much <hi>differ,</hi> becauſe the bodies of old and young men, do ſo much differ, that 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:35801:76"/>ſhould runne ſo requall a courſe as is fit for the <hi>Sympathy of Deſires</hi> which is ever betweene friends.</p>
                  <p>Their eſtates muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily bee equall, that is, their wants. For ſince no mans ſtate is ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but hee deſires ſtill to adde ſomewhat to it, in one kind or other, (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> in his opinion he yet wants) <hi>Mens</hi> eſtates are in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſſe</hi> one then another, according as their <hi>Wants</hi> are fewer, and leſſe Eſſentiall. It is fit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Eſtate of <hi>Friends</hi> ſhould bee in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Of this Community ſee an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, in the Golden Age of the Primitive Church: Acts 2.41. to the end.</note> in every thing, that reſpects the <hi>Conveniencies</hi> of Life.</p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:35801:77"/>
                  <p>But in matters of <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie,</hi> there's no ſuch Neceſſitie: for ſuppoſe there were two friends, of which, one had five hundred <hi>per ann:</hi> and the other a very little, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a diſcreet man, and out of thoſe Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which require with the Neceſſitie, as many Abilities to perform them, did ſo manage his <hi>little,</hi> that hee made it ſupply him all the Conveniences of life; there were no Neceſſitie, that hee that had the <hi>Great eſtate,</hi> ſhould ſhare it with the other. But if the one Friend ſhould chance by any misfortune to fall into miſerable want, it is fit, that the other
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:35801:77"/>ſhould releeve him, <hi>to the uttermost penny of his eſtate.</hi> For <hi>Friends,</hi> are
<note n="*" place="margin">Members ſhould have the ſame care one for another, 1 Cor. 12.25 At dum ſibi quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> plus ſatis addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt, alios praeteritac negligit. Hoc vitium <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſuperat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi: Vnde autemid, niſi a Deo, qui particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iam ſuae bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus inſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat; I. C.</note> 
                     <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> of <hi>equall Dignity,</hi> of <hi>one</hi> and <hi>the ſame Body</hi> of Friendſhip. And as no man that had one of his hands dangerouſly woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the other whole; and had in his Power ſo much Money as would ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cure the hurt hand, or buy a fine Ring for a Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of that hand that were ſound, would bee ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet as to preferre the vaine affectation of having a Gold-Ring for his ſound Finger, before the <hi>Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall benefit</hi> of recovering the decayed health of a hand: and yet no man would impoſe a neceſſitie
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:35801:78"/>upon a man that had both his hands ſound, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide a Ring, that one hand wore with the other: Iuſt ſo is it with <hi>Friends,</hi> who in points of <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ought to joyneboth their <hi>Forces</hi> to the relieving of him <hi>that wants;</hi> but in <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Superfluitie,</hi> let every man enjoy that he hath.</p>
                  <p>To conclude; <hi>True Friendſhip</hi> is the Crowne of all Morall Vertues; for Morall Vertue inſtructs a man to govern all Actions in ſuch a regular Manner, as may beſt ſerve to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſociety and mutuall Converſation amongſt men.</p>
                  <p>And as the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and perfecteſt end of
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:35801:78"/>Societie, is Friendſhip: ſo doubtleſſe that is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence and perfection of Vertue which directs a man to the Attainement of this moſt happy ſtate, and preſerves him in it. As it is the Conſummation of Vertue: ſo I deſire, it may bee of my life: which I will endeavour to governe by it. And I ſhall eſteeme my ſelfe as happy as the World can make mee, if having laid the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my life in Honeſty, and continued this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke through the <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Opinions</hi> of Men, and Chances of this World, with a perpetuall deſire of taking hold of every Opportunitie of doing
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:35801:79"/>vertuous and worthy acts, I ſhall conclude my life, enjoying and being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed of a conſtant
<note n="*" place="margin">A perfect friend is no ſhaking Reed: like Varroes Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamelos, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtantiae ſilius: but like God, who is not variable in his Love, Iam. 1.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Perfect friend,</hi> in the Noble en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſes of mutuall <hi>amity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:79"/>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="appendix">
                  <pb facs="tcp:35801:80"/>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:35801:80"/>
                  <head>Appendix of LOVE and FRIENDS: <hi>According to</hi> Ariſtotles <hi>Judgement, delivered in his ſecond Booke of Rhetorik,</hi> chap. 4.</head>
                  <p>TO Love is to wiſh well to another, for that others, not ones own ſake.</p>
                  <p>A FRIEND is hee
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:35801:81"/>that Loves, and is belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Friends,</hi> are they, that mutually love each other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Friend therefore hee is,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That rejoyces at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good.</p>
                  <p>That grieves at his hurt.</p>
                  <p>That wiſhes the ſame with us to a third, whether good or hurt.</p>
                  <p>And that is <hi>Enemy</hi> or <hi>Friend</hi> to the ſame perſon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We love them,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That have beene bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall to <hi>Us</hi> or <hi>Ours:</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, if amply, readily, or ſeaſonably.</p>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:35801:81"/>
                  <p>That are our <hi>Friends friends.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That are our <hi>Enemies enemies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That are Bountifull.</p>
                  <p>That are Valorous.</p>
                  <p>That are Iuſt.</p>
                  <p>And thoſe wee would have love Vs.</p>
                  <p>And good Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as can abide Ieſts.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as breake Ieſts.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as commend us, eſpecially, for ſomwhat that wee doubt of in our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as are neat.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as upbraid us not with our Vices, or their own benefits.</p>
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:35801:82"/>
                  <p>And ſuch as quickly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get injuries.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as leſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our errours.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as are not of ill language.</p>
                  <p>And thoſe that are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of our Vices.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as croſſe us not when wee are buſie or angry.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as are offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous towards Vs.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as profeſſe the ſame Trade or courſe of life, where they impeach not each other.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as labour for the ſame thing, when both may be ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd to tell us freely their faults, ſo it bee not in
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:35801:82"/>contempt of Vs, and the Faults ſuch, as the whole World rather than their owne Conſciences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as are indeed aſham'd to tel us their very faults.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as we would have honour us, and not any way to envie, but to imitate us.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as We would doe good to, except with greater danger or hurt to our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as continue their firme Affection to the Dead.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as ſpeak their minde.</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as are not ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible.</p>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:35801:83"/>
                  <p>And ſuch as wee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie on.</p>
                  <p>The ſeverall ſorts of <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> are <hi>Society, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, Conſanguinity, Affinity, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The things that procure love, are the beſtowing of benefits
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Freely,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Voluntarily,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Privately.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:35801:83"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35801:84"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35801:84"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tho. Wykes.</hi> R.P. <hi>Epiſc. Lond. Capell:</hi> DOMEST.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:35801:85"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35801:85"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
